<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The one good way of God contrary to the many different ways of mens making : with loving warnings, exhortations &amp; cautions to all sorts of men, concerning their souls, and to be at peace amongst themselves / by Richard Hodden.</title>
            <author>Hodden, Richard.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 185 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 39 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44035</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2283</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28665</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10736340</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10736340</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45573</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44035)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45573)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1404:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The one good way of God contrary to the many different ways of mens making : with loving warnings, exhortations &amp; cautions to all sorts of men, concerning their souls, and to be at peace amongst themselves / by Richard Hodden.</title>
                  <author>Hodden, Richard.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.C. and are to be sold by Richard Moon,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45573:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45573:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE One Good Way OF GOD: CONTRARY To the many different ways of Mens making. WITH Loving Warnings, Exhortations &amp; Cautions, to all ſorts of men concerning their ſouls, and to be at peace amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <q>By One that truly loves them in and for God.—Known by the outward name, <bibl>
                  <hi>RICHARD HODDEN.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 6.7.</hi>
               </bibl> Be not deceived, God is not mocked: whatſoever a man ſoweth, that ſhall he alſo reap, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 6.11, 12.</hi>
               </bibl> Put on the whole armour of God, that ye may be able to ſtand againſt the wiles of the Devil: for we wreſtle not with fleſh and blood, but againſt principalities, againſt powers, againſt the rulers of the darkneſs of this world, againſt ſpiritual wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in high places.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſ. 4.14.</hi>
               </bibl> That we henceforth be no more children, toſſed to and fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd carried about with every wind of doctrine, by ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſs, whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Richard Moon,</hi> Book-ſeller, in <hi>Windſtreet</hi> in <hi>Briſtol.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45573:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:45573:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Friendly Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have here made mention of the Good Cauſe and Way of God in plain words, (according to the knowledge of his Son revealed in me) with much love to all men; that they might with their eyes ſee, and with their ears hear, the voice of the beloved Son of God; be converted, healed, and live unto him in righteouſneſs and true holineſs. And if thou be willing to know this one way for thine own ſoul, (with the true ſtate thereof) turn in thy mind to the pure light of the Lord Jeſus, to the word that is neer thee, in thy mouth and in thine heart; commune there, and be ſtill to obey it, that thou maiſt know thine own Teacher, learn thine own Leſſon, feel and find how thy ſoul proſpereth and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velleth in its journey towards the holy Land of heavenly Love, and bleſſed Reſt; to enter therein, and ceaſe from thy own works, as God did from his.</p>
            <p>And thus prepared, read on conſiderately with deep ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, great dread, love and meeckneſs, that thou maiſt feel the love and favour therein, (not to get words, and thereby deceive thy ſoul) and ever mind the preſent ſtirrings in thy heart to love and long after the Lords knocking at thy door
<pb facs="tcp:45573:3"/>for thee to open, <hi>that the King of glory may come in,</hi> and ſhew thee what his good pleaſure it in thine own parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, for thy good, (without running into others conditions to looſe thine own ſtrength) that thou maiſt walk in obedience thereto, by the leading of his bleſſed ſpirit of holineſs, (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever others ſcoffingly may ſpeak thereof) and ſo feel and find what adviſeable part of the enſuing Treatiſe may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern thy preſent ſtate; and therein wait, and abide faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, until thou ſhalt hear the voice ſaying, <hi>Come up high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and then follow it: for the eternal life (here but hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at) is far from the roving wild mind, and unſtable ſoul, and cannot be truely taſted, or ſweetly ſavoured, ſo long as the ſoul remains ignorant of its ſelf and true Teacher, or beholds any created things, and mingles with them; becauſe Eternity is perfectly free from all ſimilitudes, appearances, and periſhing things, as being of and in the Father of lights, <hi>(with whom is no variableneſs, nor ſhadow of changing)</hi> whoſe pure preſence ſo raviſheth the enlightned ſouls that it deſireth nothing but union with that light, and to know and do what that willeth in him; and therein ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to bring all others into the ſame heavenly frame and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py eſtate of endleſs joy and bleſſed love, (without hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, or fear of puniſhment) wherein dependeth all the ſouls happineſs, which no man ought to ſhun, neither indeed doth, but he that is wilfully blind, willingly ignorant of the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, (the true light;) and enemy to vertue, and the health and ſafety of his own ſoul, becauſe this pure path is ready prepared, and ever open, waiting to embrace and conduct the ſoul that ſo cometh; and is ſuch as whereas the pure mind finds the entrance eaſie, plain and pleaſant, ſuch as wherein the unlearned, (fools in the worlds eſteem) and of mean capacities, cannot erre: but the worldly-wiſe, prudent and learned Clerks, may not (thereby) be acquainted
<pb facs="tcp:45573:3"/>with it, it is ſo contrary to their wiſdom; and the entrance, a ſtrait gate to them, becauſe therein their invented Arts, and earthly skill, have no place, (which they that truſt to, ſhall one day know, and pay for their credulity) though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe commendable and uſeful in the managing of earthly matters. And herein is the great mercy of Almighty God manifested in Chriſt Jeſus to ſinners, (that have long neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected his love) that the poor, the blind, the lame, and all willing, watchful, and weary ſouls, (that truly love him in his leaſt and loweſt appearance) might come to him; and in his pure path of pleaſure and light, ſee light, and finde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment, as thoſe that have gone before in owning and witneſsing his good old Cauſe in his way; as did righteous <hi>Abel, Enoch, Noah, Abraham, Moſes,</hi> the Prophets, Chriſt Jeſus himſelf, and his Diſciples, (Martyrs and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers) did, and ſtill do, to obey him in all the leadings of his love in their ſouls, and feelings of his grace and ſpiritual fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour; that they may know him more and better, and ſo grow up in him, and (by his ſpiritual nouriſhment pruning and purging, be ſitted to bring forth more fruit in moſt humble and modeſt manner of obedience, according to the farther diſcoveries of his higher glory, and be therein exerciſed, that the purchaſed inheritance of the Saints in light, and crown thereof, may be in due time received.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thy Friend, <hi>R. H.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:45573:4"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1 EPiſtle.</item>
               <item>2 Of <hi>Adam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3 Worldlings.</item>
               <item>4 Formaliſts.</item>
               <item>5 Zealots.</item>
               <item>6 Love of God.</item>
               <item>7 Jeſus Chriſt.</item>
               <item>8 Soul.</item>
               <item>9 Meditations.</item>
               <item>10 Prayer.</item>
               <item>11 Pearl.</item>
               <item>12 Converſion.</item>
               <item>13 Temptations.</item>
               <item>14 Faith in fleſhly feeling.</item>
               <item>15 Darkneſs of Soul.</item>
               <item>16 Meekneſs of Love.</item>
               <item>17 Faith in ſpiritual favour.</item>
               <item>18 Concluſion.
<list>
                     <item>Peace in all.</item>
                     <item>Humility in all.</item>
                     <item>The Croſs in all.</item>
                     <item>Tenderneſs in all.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45573:4"/>
            <head>The One Good Way of GOD, Contrary to the many different Ways of Men's Making.</head>
            <p>I Intend not here to ſay much (though ſomething may be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected) of the Manner how, Matter whereof, or Time when the Lord God formed the firſt Man <hi>Adam,</hi> and breathed into him the breath of life, whereby he became a living ſoul; or how long he abode in that innocent life, of obedience, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the abilities thereby given him, to converſe with God, and give names to the other Creatures, according to their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; how God made him a meet helper; how the Devil (as a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>btil Serpent) prevailed with the woman, and both with <hi>Adam,</hi> to learn and ſtrive to be kingly, potent, and skilful to reign, and rule over the Love and meekneſs of God, and by ſelf-will to look out (with a laſtful minde) after what was forbidden him, and to take content in the viſible things of this Earthly Creation, and be ambitious and covetous thereof (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the devils Kingdom conſiſts) for which the ſerpent was rejected, and alſo man caſt out of Paradice, from the ſweet preſence of God, into this viſible world, to take his portion (where his proud heart had choſen it) in the knowledge of good and evil, inventions and luſts, without and contrary to God; and how this begot in him an evil opinion of God, trouble of Mind and condemnation in himſelf; whereby ſorrow of ſoul ſeiſed on him, love, meekneſs and humanity was loſt, and he was dead unto God, and all good, but alive to every luſt and fleſhly delight, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly as a devil, and outwardly as a beaſt (by his ſo abuſing his truſt) inſomuch, that he then eſteemed God (who before was his life and delight) as his enemy, and became affraid of him, and could in no wiſe change his mind to love and truſt God again, (though the Lord God changed not) but covered himſelf with outward things, as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:45573:5"/>Fig-leaves, and hid himſelf from the preſence of God amongſt the trees, when he heard his voice there in the cool of the day: Or how <hi>Adam</hi> excuſed himſelf concerning his nakedneſs, his fear, or the prevalency of the temptation, by reaſon of his light or looſe-mindedneſs; how he was driven out of the Garden, and Cherubims with a flaming ſword ſet up to turn every way, and keep the way of the tree of life: or what was figured out thereby, concerning mans having his choſen portion in this world of his own will, ſelfiſh wiſdom, and earthly glory, by which ſin entred, and death by ſin came over all men, inaſmuch as all have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and come ſhort of the glory of God, by turning his truth into a lye, worſhipping and ſerving the Creature inſtead of the Creator, (who is God over all, and rich unto all that call upon him) and ſo are become enemies in their minds through evil works, and to every good work re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probares; and no way to be recovered, but through the love and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der mercy of the Lord God, (ſo much abuſed) in the then promiſed ſeed, to bruiſe the Serpents head, deſtroy his ſinful will and wiſdom in mans mortal body, and reſtore him again to God, (from whom by tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion he fell) by turning his mind into the eternal counſel &amp; will, and thereby bringing in an everlaſting righteouſneſs, in the new man, crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in Chriſt Jeſus, by the ſpirit of holineſs, to good works, and walk in them, to the reſtauration of all things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But of theſe things briefly, that I may be more large touching the end of mans Creation, and his duty in relation thereto, in which <hi>Abel</hi> offered an acceptable ſacrifice, <hi>Snoch</hi> walked with God, pleaſed him, was tranſlated, and not found (by any tentation) for God took him into the eternal heavenly hearing, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taſting, feeling of love, and firm obedience, wherein the Lord GOD accepts every man that ſo comes unto him in Chriſt Jeſus, (the ſame unchangeable way, truth and life) as babes and ſucklings, and ſo receive his kingdom as little children, and (in the new ſpiritual birth, and by the ſincere milk of the word) grow up in him, and become wholly his, and for him, in his eternal counſel and will, and have their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations in heaven, hating the fleſh, and drinking the blood of the Son of God, and partaking of his holineſs, and glory, wherein the Tempter cannot find them, though he may contend as he did about the body of <hi>Moſes.</hi> But though <hi>Enoch</hi> ſo walked with God, and after him, <hi>Noah</hi> was ſingular in his generation, yet (as it is written) <hi>The wickedneſs of man was great in the earth, the imaginations and thoughts of his hears onely evil continually; for all fleſh had corrupted their way; the earth was filled with violence: inſomuch that the Lord repented that he had made man on the earth:</hi> but man (by his Deed cauſing this) repented not to give glory to God, (in any general way) yet for all this, the Lords love and long ſuffering waited in the days of <hi>Noah,</hi> and afterwards ſuffered the evil manners of his people (the natural ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi>) in the wilderneſs, and endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as now he doth) the <hi>veſſels of wrath fitted for deſtruction,</hi> (by unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, hardneſs of heart, and rebellion againſt him) that ſpend their times, and weary their wits, about eating, drinking, revelling, dancin
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45573:5"/>and ſerving their luſts of all kinds, with violence, in vicious living, as if that were the very end of mans Creation. The Lords love in tende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring redemption, his outward chaſtiſements, inward ſmitings, and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings in his beloved ſervants, whereby he warneth all men to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to take heed how they allow or plead for their ſins, (as moſt do) ſaying, They muſt have their ſins while their ſouls are in their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies; or (as ſome ſpeak) until their laſt gaſp: but it were better ſaid by ſuch men, That they may, but will not, come to Chriſt to be led otherwiſe by his light and ſpirit of holineſs, to be cleanſed from all un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs: were they but willing to follow him in his bleſſed foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps before the Lords jealouſie and wrath be yet farther kindled againſt them, that ſo wax old in their evil ways by cuſtom therein; ſpecially in theſe times of tryal, while he is working wonders in the earth, and delivering his choſen ones, avenging his elect, (that cry to him) exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the judgement written, as well for the rebellious, as for proving and purging his own houſhold-ſervants; or think the time not near when he ſhall ſay, <hi>They are turned to their idols, let them alone. They that are filthy, let them be filthy ſtill. Why ſhould they be ſmitten any more? Let them go to the gods they have ſerved. Give them their portion,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>As ignorance is ever the mother of Devotion in erroneous principles, Opinions and Practiſes; ſo conſequently it is of Diviſions in thoſe er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous-paths, whereby wilful ignorance is turned into immodeſt Zeal, and haſty frowardneſs to make by-ways, with gaudy and guilded ſhews for others to fall down before, and worſhip: but my buſineſs being (here ſpecially) to give ſome directions to weary Travellers that are going out of their way, and yet would know, and enter the door of mercy, and hope to find refreſhment for their ſouls; and likewiſe to the rebellious, (that are in bondage) that the Lord God might dwell amongſt them, and bring them alſo into his fold, and freedom of glorious liberty with the ſons of God; and therefore briefly touch and paſs over the many by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways that lead to, and thorow Preſumption into Deſpair, and thence in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to endleſs miſery; as the way of <hi>Cain, Nimrod,</hi> the old world, <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres, Iſhmael, Eſau, Core</hi> and his company, <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abibu, Balaam,</hi> and ſundry other falſe Prophets, Apoſtates and Perſecutors, as recorded in holy Scripture, over-many here to mention, and at this time too ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtly in uſe to be now hid.</p>
            <p n="3">III. The covetous prophane worldly men, in their ſeveral ways, chuſe their portions in this world, their great deſires, hopes, fears and cares, being to get, ſave and poſſeſs an earthly inheritance; which is their portion, and their hearts there alſo: ſome taking liberty (in the will of Satan and the fleſh) to uſe (or rather abuſe) the outward things upon their own luſts, without any touch of Conſcience, as being unwilling
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45573:6"/>to know what Conſcience, and the light therein, means, leſt it ſhould hinder their earthly happineſs of glorying in their ſhame, as men not in their right minds, but bereaved of their wits; not knowing what they are, of whom they are, to whom they belong, what their buſineſs is here, or how to gain content in anything; but every Toy diſquiets their minds, every filthy luſt takes hold of them, and gets dominion o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, leads them captive; and they ſay they cannot help it: ſome adding, that if God had given them grace to forſake their evil ways, (as he hath done to ſome others) then they ſhould be happy, and gladly leave their ſinful courſes; and when God giveth them grace, they will, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Now to ſuch I ſay, They ſpeak truely, (but very wickedly) that they have no grace; and therefore none they will have, (though the grace of God hath appeared to all men) but they continue ſtill in their filthy love, and delight in their luſts, and that becauſe they diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able themſelves to receive grace, and neither wait to be prepared for the drawings of God in them, nor take any heed to his leading or light that would ſhew them better, but reſiſt all; ſo that they ſeldome feel a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glimpſe of the light of Chriſt, neither are willing to ſuffer it to reſt in, or ſhine into, their ſouls, leſt it ſhould draw them from the great love and liking of this world, and the luſts that ſeem ſo ſweet to them. But, Do they ſay they want grace to reſiſt ſin, and tentations thereto, that do preſently yeild themſelves to ſin upon the motions thereof? Theſe men have grace truely offered to them, but they withſtand it, and turn it into wantonneſs, and reſiſt the true light and holy Spirit when it moveth and ſtriveth with them, (as ſometime did the old world) where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it becomes as natural to ſuch men to commit ſin, as the Ox to drink in water; and therefore think it impoſſible to withſtand it; but it is by reaſon of their cuſtom therein, and willingneſs thereto, which doth ſo weaken and enfeeble their wills and affections to grace, that they feel not the vertue thereof to reſiſt the Devil, or ſin, when he offers it to the ſoul: and when they do feel inward ſmitings in their Conſciences, or as a heavy weight upon them, they preſently (to quiet their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences) flee to their vain pleaſures, and luſtful practiſes; even as beaſts and Sodomites, to eat and drink, and riſe up to play; fill themſelves with worldly ſolace, and leave tokens of their jollity behind them; from whence that general Queſtion ariſeth, <hi>Do you love this meat, or drink? this or the other outward thing?</hi> &amp;c. about which luſts, many do ſo mightily ſpend their ſtrength, and employ their wits, in ſtriving to get needleſs wealth, to ſatisfie this love, this luſt, this god their bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, (wherein they glory) which tends to their utter loſs in ſpiritual things; and that when they have over-much, unleſs they would employ it better, and alſo caſt it off, and detract from their deſires, inordinate affections, loves and likings that keep them from the love of God, ſight and feeling of Gods grace, and way of reſtauration to the heavenly my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries of his glorious Kingdom; all bodily things being for ſupport of bodily ſtrength, (as phyſick for health) with much Caution, leſt
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45573:6"/>Iuſt ſtep in with the uſe: ſo could <hi>Paul</hi> beat down his body; and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers following his example therein, as he followed Jeſus Chriſt, to the glory of God the Father.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. O ye Formaliſts, that have (in theſe days) your ways in the aiery Element, without footing or foundation; that turn any way with every wind, not knowing whither you go, becauſe darkneſs hath blinded your eyes, and ſloth ſo poſſeſs'd your ſouls, that you are unfree and afraid to have your eyes opened in the light, leſt it ſhould prove to your loſs in earthly things, and therefore do neglect the light, and ſilence the voyce of Jeſus Chriſt in your own and others Conſciences, by your for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal and fleſhly inventions of Conformity, and bodily exerciſes, (that all are to periſh with the uſing) being (as it is written) <hi>after the doctrines and commandments of men,</hi> &amp;c. from whence ſpring up the deviſed ſnares and gins to catch the innocent, and Non-conformiſts, that are not of your aiery minds; without conſidering the commands of Chriſt Jeſus, (the Lord of the harveſt) who ſaid, Let the tares and wheat grow toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (in the world) until the harveſt; and again in theſe words, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> would that men ſhould do unto you, ſo do you unto them:</hi> or how he pleaſech reſpectively to carry on his great work of ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ls, to reform them into faith and ſpiritual feeling; neither yet how you your ſelves (or ſome of you) are but newly releaſed from under the yoke of your bondage, and ſuddenly ſtep up, upon a ſtage of this world, (to ſhew your ſelves for a little ſeaſon) ſhould not in any wiſe lay a (like, or greater) yoke of bondage upon the necks of others, then you your ſelves were able to bear: and eſpecially in theſe tranſient times, when (as it is written) the holy God is <hi>pouring contempt upon all fleſh;</hi> and theſe fading glories are vaniſhing away, ready to be left by you, or ſnatcht from you before you have any firm hold of them: but times and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are all in the Lords hands, and his ſecrets with his ſaints; and therefore (in love to your ſouls) conſider well your way, and be not high-minded, but fear before the God of heaven; and learn of him to be wiſe in this your day of tryal, to underſtand what the good will of the Lord is reſpectively to you; and let not love and meekneſs be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtered by any exalted, peeviſh, wrathful ſpirit of contention in you, for he is now proving you, that you might know what is in your own hearts, and that others might ſee whether you will indeed, truly incline your ſouls to him and his ſervice; ſo to act, as you ſeem to pray, to have his <hi>will done in earth, as it is in heaven,</hi> &amp;c. who will no more ſpare you then he hath done others, in caſe you be found in their foot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteps, contrary to his one good way, truth and life, which thoſe that have truly taſted the ſweetneſs of, cannot neglect, whatever others do; for the reaſonable ſervice is (as it is written) not a conforming to this world, but a being transformed by the renewing of the mind. To prove what that good, and acceptable, and perfect will of God is, whereby he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forms
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45573:7"/>mens ſouls through faith (as pleaſeth him) into a perfect in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſavour, taſte, feeling, and wiſe skill, which the holy Ghoſt teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth and planteth in the powers of the ſoul, whereby he requites no hard, harth, or intricate ſervice, but what is according to right reaſon, and the knowledge thereof to be received in his own light, and ſpiritual leading in every mans conſcience, there to ariſe, and his enemies be ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, as he transformeth and reneweth the mind, according to his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed will of heavenly love; and the contrary thereto is onely unreaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, unrighteous, intolerable and abominable to God, as that which enforceth men (of corrupt and unſtable minds) to formalities and hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, whereof enſueth condemnation in themſelves, to their ſouls, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many other miſchiefs and miſeries to mankinde; for what is out of faith, is ſin, both in the commander and actor; and <hi>if the heart condema, God is greater, and knoweth all: and who ſhall juſtifie where he condemns?</hi> and (as it is written) <hi>Bleſſed and happy is he that condemns not himſelf in the thing that he alloweth,</hi> and contrarily; which ought to be well heeded, and warily obſerved by all men; and is by thoſe that are willing to know and perform the great truſt repoſed in them concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their own ſouls, as knowing that they muſt give an account of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to God, and ought not to truſt their ſouls with others, that have other ends then for the Lords ſervice, and learned Arts, whereby to call good evil, and evil good, put darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, as blind men, or with their eyes ſhut, and unwilling to know the light of life, and leading of the holy Spirit of truth, as if (as the fool ſaid in his heart) there were no God, or not deſiring the knowledge of his way; and yet concerning the things of this world, cry, Give, give, more, more, when they have not rightly learned how to uſe that they have.</p>
            <p n="5">V. You that are ſtrict and zealous Profeſſors in your ways, ſhould ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to be quiet in your ſelves, and with others: you have a zeal as for God, but not according to knowledge of him, (as a fire of love in you kindled by the holy Ghoſt) and therefore you are ſuch, and ſo diverſly opinionated, without unity or order amongſt your ſelves; but one fort contending for the Monſter Uniformity, another for their new-made Faith, a third for their dead, dumb, and empty ordinances, and each im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleading others, and employing your ſelves (like <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abibu,</hi> or <hi>Core</hi> and his company) in kindling and offering ſtrange fires before the Lord, and reſiſting the truth taught in the light of Chriſt by his bleſſed Spirit which leads into all truth, (as <hi>Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> ſometime withſtood <hi>Moſes</hi>) but your deeds are ſo manifeſt, and you ſtopt and repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in your inward and outward parts, ſo as not like much farther to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, are again (in love as heretofore) warned to turn in your minds to him that there ſmiteth for amendment that a remnant of you (forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the ſparks of their own kindling) may be purged, puriſhed, and brought forth as gold tryed and ſaved by that conſuming fire which burns,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45573:7"/>and waſts all ſin our of obedient ſouls, with the fleſhly loves and lovers thereof; ſo as there may be no more miſ-judging by private and perverſe ſpirits of ignorance, weakneſs, or thick darkneſs, that cannot compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the deep things of God, but do turn the minds out of the true light of Jeſus Chriſt, (wherein his ſervants ſee light to walk that pure path of holineſs in him) to glory in words, emptineſs and vanity of your wills, bodily wits, and works, (as did the former perſecuters of Chriſt Jeſus) not wiſely heeding the Lords hand, whereby he is reſtoring all things into the glorious liberty of his ſons and daughters, and how he therefore now ſhakes the earth and heavens alſo; which ſhould abate the edge of mens earthly appetites, (accompanied with ſuch ſtrange and hideous effects) and would, if they knew any thing of the Lords pure and powerful workings, or of the times and ſeaſons, or were but near ripe for truth, and apt to the kingdom of God; and would take ſuch off from expecting greater ſignes and wonders, or acting another thing by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſpirit of private interpretation, (different from the Lords purpoſe ſo many ways manifeſted;) and therefore it is evident that ſuch men are ſick, weak, or fallen aſleep; ſo that they cannot diſcern the Lords body, his truth, and true worſhippers, nor other things that differ.—And though you may not be competent Judges in ſpiritual matters, yet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, is it righteous or reaſonable, that thoſe who are either meerly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal or have not yet received ſo much as the bare preſence of the holy Spirit in grace, ſhould judge others that are ſealed with the Spirit of promiſe, baptiſed and made to drink into that one Spirit which judgeth all things, and ſo are partakers of the divine nature of the immortal and inviſible God? Have you never read how the Lords praiſe is perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the mouths of his babes and ſucklings? and that whoſoever doth not receive the kingdom of God as a little Childe, ſhall in no wiſe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therein? or how the myſteries of that kingdom are hid from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed to ſuch babes? or how the halt, lame and blind, (whom you deſpiſe) do enter, while you your ſelves and others art ſhut out, and the rich ſent empty away? Remember that Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſt Jeſus, (to men of your ſort) ſaying, <hi>Waſh the inſide, that the out may be clean alſo.</hi> It is high time for you to be willing to put away the evil of your doings, and yeild to his light, and leading of his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, that your ſouls may be prepared and fitted to feel and know him as <hi>God equal with the Father,</hi> (ſpiritually) to clenſe you from all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs; and then you will not ſuppoſe that any good thing of him can make you happy, but what is ſo revealed, and wrought in you; or be ignorant of the danger of reſiſting, or neglecting ſuch divine ſtirrings in your ſouls, by any your exquiſite Arts, natural Reaſons, or bodily Wits, as ſome do, who are ſo much thereby deceived, that they think they are not deceived. You may read likewiſe of ſome that had travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led pretty far in outward Ordinances, been baptiſed with water, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and yet not heard that there is an holy Ghoſt; and ſuch in thoſe days, are not a few, that have their cars ſtopped with dumb and deadly ſounds
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45573:8"/>of words, or thereby become ſo dull of hearing, that they hearken not to the <hi>voice of the Charmer, though he charm never ſo wiſely;</hi> nor are got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten one ſtep farther then thoſe that had not heard of an holy Ghoſt, (though they can talk much of him by what they have read, or others told them:) and, <hi>how then ſhould they believe on him of whom they have not heard?</hi> ſpecially while they are ſo willingly led by ſuch ignorant talking, that ſo dulls them, and hinders their heeding of the true light, and hearing what the holy Spirit ſaith, and how he revealeth the deep things of God to all watchful and willing ſouls; ſo that ſuch have their loves to, and their faith and lives in, mans wiſdom, and ſeldom (or never) come to the love of God, indeed and in truth, but remain vain and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly talkers and contenders about words, queſtions, and outward things, and would make themſelves love God by their own ſtrength and wiſdom; which may not be, though they ſhould act therein never ſo violently, as it were to pull God out of heaven to them by their ſtrivings, pantings and burſtings out into heat in their devoted zeal: for though ſuch ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe in their thoughts and hearts they love God, and alſo reſolve ſo to do, and for his ſake to ſuffer death; yet theſe mens love (in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) is neither truely ſo, nor is any ſtrength ſo asked by them to ſtand therein; for ſuch ſouls have but either received that gift of love through Chriſt as a man, or they have it not, but would have it; and ſo ſtrive in their own ſtrength to feel the love of God, but come not to a waiting in the light to ſee and know their own ſouls, nor themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy and unable to do any good thing, think a good thought, or in the leaſt meaſure to move towards God, or prepare their own hearts for him, or ſee their own miſerable, blind and naked condition, as dead in ſins and treſpaſſes, waiting at the Pool to receive help and healing by the Angels moving of the water, as the Lords free gift of love to eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal life; which is the way for them to come to the ſight of Jeſus Chriſt, as being all to them, and working all in them; and therefore not to ſtrive outwardly, but quietly wait, and ask nothing but the gifts of love, that they might be touched and taught of him, to ſee God by his bleſſed light, and gracious preſence; and then love him by his own gift of love ſo received through patient ſuffering, as wrought in their ſouls by the holy Ghoſt, without bodily ſtrength, or earthly skill; theſe being the means whereby ſouls are made ſo meek and obedient, that they work not of themſelves at all by bodily wit or exerciſe, but freely ſuffer the holy Ghoſt to will and to do in them, and with them, as beſt pleaſeth him, for the working of their ſouls into faith and feeling of his love by degrees, without outward noiſe or ſtrivings about it; for Chriſts Voice was not heard in the ſtreet; it is a ſoft and ſtill voice to be heard in ſilence, and felt of all the ſenſes and powers of the ſoul, and is very ſweet to all ſavoury minds that have waited for him; and they that ſo wait long, and covet af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fruits of the Spirit, and ſow thereto, ſhall much encreaſe therein, But as this is not by bodily exerciſe, ſo it may not be by reſting in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual employment, already done, but a <hi>preſſing forward toward the mark
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45573:8"/>of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus;</hi> and ever following that they feel, to grow therein towards perfection; for otherwiſe there will be a ſudden ſettling upon the old Lees, and ſo a declining to loſs, and the end without profit or comfort: as ſome Apoſtates who have ſaid they have gone round, back again, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo loſt not onely their hold of perfection, but their firſt love, and leading principle of God in them; for there is firſt a beginning with rude ſouls, and a change of the mind in the working of faith; and then faith worketh by love, and after that by the more ſtrong, clear and pure ſtirrings (as felt in all active ſouls) towards that life of perfect love: for though the body of ſin be at firſt ſeen in the light, then debaſed, and in ſome ſuddenly crucified; yet it will be ſeen, felt, and laboured in, and againſt, until full victory be obtained: as the beloved <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, by his <hi>rejoycing in Chriſt Jeſus, he died dayly;</hi> whereby the old feeling of the body of ſin comes to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, and the ſoul brought into a new gracious feeling by the opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Spirit, to grow up in him who is the head of all prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and powers.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. Theſe things being ſo, it highly concerns every man (reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctively) to weigh, and warily conſider his own way, ſtation and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and to prize the time and abilities that the Lords love in Chriſt Jeſus hath allotted him, to wait and watch for his converſion, reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and ſalvation, and to account the time (miſpent and irrecove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably paſt) ſufficient to have done the will of the fleſh, in thinking his own thoughts, ſpeaking his own words, and acting contrary to the eternal counſel and will; and that the preſent time is onely mans to make his uſe of, (not knowing what ſhall be to morrow) and the loſs of what is paſt, will be his greateſt grief, as his ignorant ſoul comes to ſee it ſelf, its ſins and duty; or otherwiſe (as Chriſt ſaid of <hi>Judas) better to him he had never been born:</hi> Whereof I onely query, (as the beloved <hi>Peter</hi>) What ſhall the end be, of thoſe that obey not the Goſpel of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt; but take pleaſure in unrighteouſneſs, and mind not the Lords love in drawing them, or their duties in a willing yeilding, and ſuitable ſubjection thereto? For great was the love of the Lord God in creating man after his own image and likeneſs, with a ſoul fair, clean, and fit for his ſervice and glory; and yet greater (when man had proudly departed from that holy and happy condition, and made himſelf unfree and unfit to embrace that love, and ſerve that end) in commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, promiſing and ſetting forth his love again in his own onely Son, to reſtore man, and bring him back into God, (from whom he ſo wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and wickedly departed by the enticement of the Devil) and thereby to free him from the ſnares thereof, and pains due therefore; and yet his eſpecial and greateſt love, is to be felt, taſted, and ſweetly ſavoured in his free cleanſing of mans ſoul by the gift of the holy Ghoſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it becomes to be conformed to the likeneſs of his dear Son; by which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45573:9"/>love, he giveth of his Godhead to every obedient and clean ſoul, (that comes to will and to do of his good pleaſure) as a fit veſſel and temple for the holy Ghoſt to dwell in, and walk in: which all his ſons and daughters (that are heirs of this ſalvation) do right-well know, and therein are made willing and obedient, ready and diligent to help all others (what they may) to come to the ſame happy condition of bleſſed love and heavenly ſweetneſs, that all things may be reſtored to their firſt and primitive purity, and the great mercy and love of the Lord ſeen to, and felt by all his creatures; for whom he taketh care in their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive kinds, feeding the Ravens, clothing the Lilies, and much more the obedient ſoul that is of his own breath, and waits upon him by his Spirit, being plain and ſimple in the truth, and willing to do all things in the eternal will, ever waiting to live always in his light of love by every word that proceeds out of his mouth, until he be ſwallowed up of the divine will, and inexpreſſible goodneſs and wiſdom; and ſo ſettled in his reſt, (with a ſober and chaſte mind) as to be preſerved from touching any thing that defiles, or wherein the ſoul feels not the pure love, meek motion, and heavenly life of Jeſus Chriſt above all outward appearances, likeneſſes or forms of words; and as it is contrary to, and envyed of, all natural ſelfiſhneſs.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. In the next place, truely to know this one Lord Jeſus Chriſt come in the fleſh, as the new and living way to the Father, the <hi>Imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuel, (God with us)</hi> making the atonement by the blood of his Croſs, to have all things ſubject unto him, his ſervants in him, and he in them; which is the great myſterie of godlineſs, hid from Ages and Generations, until the fulneſs of time, and then <hi>manifeſted in the fleſh, juſtified in the ſpirit, believed on in the world, and received up into glory;</hi> which none of the wiſe men of this world ever knew, or can know by all their learned skill of earthly wiſdom; nor any man that lives after the fleſh, or ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth himſelf with hearing, reading, telling, or talking of him, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning what he or his Apoſtles did, ſaid, or ſuffered; as thoſe that vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly take his Name into their mouths, (on moſt occaſions of their inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ways) but know him not, neither by his divine Nature nor Name, nor how God and man became one Chriſt Jeſus, how that which may be known of God is manifeſt in man, how he is the <hi>wonderful, counſellor, The mighty God, The Prince of peace: The Author and Finiſher of our faith:</hi> how he ſaves his people from their ſins, is the Reconciler without impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of ſin: how he is formed in his ſervants, and cleanſeth them by his blood from all ſin and unrighteouſneſs: how they take up the croſs and follow him, or what the croſs is; how the body becomes dead be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſin, and the ſpirit alive for righteouſneſs ſake: how they are members of his body, of his fleſh, and of his bones: how he is their <hi>Leader, and captain of ſalvation, made perfect through ſufferings:</hi> how they are baptiſed into his death, and ſaved by his life; how the Union
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45573:9"/>is perfected in all the parts and members of his body the Church: what the Church is, or how his Body; or what it is to eat his fleſh, and drink his blood; without which (as himſelf ſaid) we have no life in us: how <hi>every knee ſhall bow to him, of things in heaven, in earth, and under the earth; and confeſs that Jeſus Chriſt is Lord, to the glory of God the Father:</hi> how he is that <hi>bleſſed and onely Potentate, King of kings, and Lord of lords: The head of all thrones and dominions, and every name that is named,</hi> &amp;c. And therefore (not knowing him) cannot worſhip him accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly. Neither are ſuch willing to become obedient to him in his light that maketh all things manifeſt, naked and bare; whereby he brings every ſecret thing to light, and paſſeth judgement upon the tranſgreſſing nature, and bruiſeth the branches of it with every luſt of the fleſh, luſt of the eyes, and pride of life, (that are not of the Father, but of the world) nor to know him the <hi>Healer and Maker up of the breach, the Repairer of the ancient path to walk in;</hi> by cleanſing mens ſouls, that are full filthy, while they remain ignorant of him, or have any fleſhly appetite, luſt, or like deſire alive in them, whereby the fair pearl is blemiſhed; and much more filthy, when their ſouls are taken up with a full love and liking of this world, and wholly overcome by the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual and fleſhly part, that they chuſe it, and delight therein as the full reſt of their hearts; ſo that they feel no liquor of life, or ſweetneſs of grace ſtirring them to loath what their fleſh liketh; nor to deſire that heavenly food of their ſouls: ſo they do not bear the image of ſin, but are born, and carryed with it, and of it, and feel no ſtrength but in it, nor no will to leave it, but yeild thereto with all ready forwardneſs.— But Jeſus Chriſt is the food of all hungry ſouls; and through him, in him, and by him, are ſuch ſouls reformed and reſtored into their firſt and fair likeneſs of God, in righteouſneſs and true holineſs; and ſo is the new man created in Chriſt Jeſus to good works to walk in them by the Divine will, and quickning Spirit; whereby the flaming ſword comes to be removed, and the everlaſting gate opened to all willing and watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſouls to enter thereat into the heavenly and endleſs life, where Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is the Door, the Porter and Receiver, always waiting ready to imbrace the ſouls that ſo watch, pray, wait and attend to be (here in this life) reformed by his Spirit into his likeneſs and love, to live by the words of his mouth, as ſwallowed up of the Divine will of inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſweetneſs, and ſo walk in the Spirit of love and meekneſs, with ſober and chaſte minds, as the Lords free-men, without handling or touching any unclean thing that defiles, or where in their ſouls feel not the pure love, meek motion, and holy life of Jeſus Chriſt above all ſhadows, types, figures, forms, or fleſhly things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that think they love Jeſus Chriſt, and know him, to whom he may truly ſay, <hi>I know you not; depart from me, ye are workers of iniquity.</hi>— Though they may have attained to a fleſhly knowledge of him, by ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, thinking, and faſhioning him in themſelves, (with their minds, thoughts, affections, deſires, cares, and bodily wits) and ſo ſuppoſe they
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45573:10"/>love, fear, ſerve and worſhip him as a man like themſelves, (yet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſin) that God is wroth with them as a man that is offended, that Chriſt died for their ſins, and therefore they fall down at his feet with ſorrow of heart, crying for mercy and pardon; and (like the five foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Virgins) ſuppoſe they are ready for him, have good truſt in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and ſo reverence him, and fear before him; and thereupon do verily believe they ſo know and worſhip him, becauſe they feel their hearts moved and ſtirred with love to him, and deſire of him.—But this is not the worſhip in ſpirit and truth, which he expects, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts; for all this while theſe worſhippers know not their own ſouls, nor God in Chriſt Jeſus reconciling them to himſelf; nor have they any Oyl in their lamps, or ſweet liquor of life ſuppling their ſouls; for the Lord Jeſus is not ſeen, much leſs known and worſhipped by mens imaginations; for the earthly nature cannot receive, retain, or bear this heavenly new wine.—So there was a time when Chriſt Jeſus told his Diſciples he had <hi>many things to ſay unto them, but they could not then bear them;</hi> and yet being upright in hearts to the Lord, he is pleaſed ſo to temper, ſtrengthen and comfort them with ſuch an inward behold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that they forſake ſins, and the great love of this world, whereby the inviſible light of his Godhead is ſomewhat ſhadowed to the inner eye of their ſouls, under the bedily likeneſs of Chriſts fleſhly holineſs; and may be in ſo great love, that it ſlayeth all wicked love in their ſouls, and ſtrengthens them to ſuffer freely for him; and yet this over-ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowing of their ſouls, (whereby they are kept from the great love of the world) is onely as a ſhadow of the inviſible light of the Godhead and manhood united, and lightly touching the ſerious and devour ſoul; whereof the Prophet ſpake, as being under the ſhadow of his ſpiritual wings, (or manhood) and yet this is but Chriſts love received into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens dark minds and imaginations, though it be that condition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto thouſands (profeſſing Chriſtianity) have not yet attained, though they pretend much, and ſeem to teach others alſo.—But it is faith and ſpiritual feeling of Jeſus Chriſt which purifieth the heart, and whereby the ſoul comes to underſtand his ſpiritual love in the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, (as Chriſt ſaid) <hi>I in them, and thou in me,</hi> and to be made perfect in one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to which all bodily beholdings are but as means directing mens minds to the light, and thereby their ſouls to a ſerious conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the wonderful love, goodneſs, power and wiſdom mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted in the manhood of Chriſt ſpiritually.—And ſo it is like <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha</hi> loved him, and laboured in outward ſervice for him, and that with hearty affections: but <hi>Mary choſe the better part;</hi> ſhe received and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced him with more pure affections, and retained him in her beart.— <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> loved Chriſt well before his paſſion of bodily death, but her love was much bodily, and little ſpiritually, for ſhe loved him not as God before, though her thoughts and affections were ſet upon him; in which affections, (or actions, expreſſing her love) Chriſt condemns her not in that time, (ſo far as we find) but after when he was riſen from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45573:10"/>death, and appeared unto her, ſhe would have reverenced him with ſuch a manner of love as ſhe did before, and then Chriſt forbad her, ſaying, <hi>Touch me not;</hi> as, look not on me with a fleſhly eye to reſt therein, for ſo I am not aſcended to my Father, nor equal to the Father ſo; but now, love me as I am one with the Father, in the form of the Godhead; know, love and worſhip me as God, and man like God, ſo to be with me; love and worſhip me onely for that I am God, that took the nature of man; and therefore receive and embrace me as God in thine heart, and in thy love of me, and worſhip me in the enlightned underſtanding of thy ſoul, as Jeſus Chriſt, God and man; the ſaving truth, goodneſs, and light of bleſſed life, and ſpiritual joy: and ſo Chriſt Jeſus promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to come unto his Diſciples, and be with them by his holy Spirit, (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter given them) with power from on high to teach them all things, and lead them into all truth: the which heavenly gift of holineſs and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, few have yet attained to in theſe latter times, ſince the Apoſtacy: and therefore thoſe ſouls (that have not attained to this ſpiritual under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of him through his grace) are to wait in his light, with pure affections of fervent love, until more grace be freely given unto them, and not to over-run the conditions wherein they are, but ſtay therein until they ſhall reſpectively feel a better revealed in them; ſtill mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that all ſpiritual gifts are felt and taſted in the powers of the ſouls; chiefly, in love and ſpiritual underſtanding, but not in imaginations through the ſtrength of the body, or bodily wits, which are not ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al feelings, and at moſt but outward tokens of ſpiritual inward feelings in the powers of their ſouls, where the holy Ghoſt hath lighted their reaſons, and kindled their affections with his bleſſed Preſence ſo clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in fervent love, that they immediately thereby received the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſpiritual truth, and perfect love, with an outward ſhewing of of the inward feeling of ſpiritual grace.—And as it was in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Diſciples, ſo it is now in other like-perfect ſouls, viſited and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed within by the holy Ghoſt, whereby there is an outward feeling of the inward grace, and the body made obedient (thereby) to the Spirits moving and leading; without fainedneſs or fancie of imagination.— And he is no ſpiritual man that hath not thus learned Chriſt, or is taught his leſſon by him in like ſpiritual wiſe; nor any way qualified to judge of ſpiritual matters, but muſt conſequently erre in his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and mar all he meddles with; and not know how, or wherein he ſo erreth, much leſs how to amend his own crrours; and how then ſhall he reform others, but as a blind man may judge of colours, becauſe theſe ſpiritual things are above the ſight of his carnal eye, ſo that he perceiveth them not that hath not the ſpiritual eye of his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing opened? and how then ſhould he open the Scriptures, that (as Chriſt ſaid) neither knows them, nor the power of God, or be skill'd in the uſe of his ſpiritual Weapons, his warfare or work to be done in his Vineyard, or know the kingdom, power or glory of God, whereto all true ſervice tends?—For, (as it is written) <hi>The natural man underſtands not
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45573:11"/>the things</hi> of the Spirit <hi>of God:</hi> but they are fooliſhneſs to him; for it is the ſpiritual man that judgeth all things, and is judged of no man, becauſe his life is hid with God in Chriſt, as taken from the earth, and unknown to the world, but well known to God; and is ſo reformed in ſoul, that he feels the leaſt fleſhly ſtirring in him, and condemns it, and loaths it in his heart, and ever fleeth to God for ſtrength againſt all ſuch motions; and loves not his life to attain the life eternal, but is paſſive in every thing; a man of ſorrows and ſufferings, as his Lord Jeſus was, and left him an enſample to follow him therein.</p>
            <p>Seeing the buſineſs in hand is of ſoul-concernment, it is abſolutely neceſſary, that the ſoul ſhould know it ſelf, with the facultie, vertues and powers thereof, by its turning into, and watchful keeping in its pure principle of the light of Chriſt Jeſus in the Conſcience, to love that light, and obſerve its motions as it ſhall be led by the holy Spirit into all truth, and thereby reſtored into its primitive purity, fit to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the ſweet preſence of God, as <hi>Adam</hi> did before his diſobedience.— For a miſerable and wretched man is he that knoweth not the workings, worth and worthineſs of his own ſoul, (the firſt leſſon to be learned in Chriſts ſchool, as the trade of his youth) it being the moſt excellent Creature that the Lord God formed for his ſervice and glory, (whereto nothing can give true content, ſatisfaction or reſt, but God onely; and therefore neither to love nor deſire any thing but him) for other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe he cannot come to know the Spirit of God, and what it willeth, worketh, or would work in him; how it ſtriveth, how it is grieved, how quenched, how he ſearcheth all things, (<hi>even the deep things of God:</hi>) how he dwelleth in man, how he witneſſeth with mans ſpirit, or how he baptiſeth into the one body; how the excellent myſteries of divine love are revealed (to the obedient and clean ſoul) by the holy Ghoſt; or how ſo to live and walk in the Spirit, as not to fulfil the luſts of the fleſh. This living ſoul is not any corporeal ſubſtance, but a life invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, (as God is inviſible) for it is of the breath of God, and ſo is Gods, (in an eſpecial manner) that by its vertue beareth up the body, and quickneth it, and ſo the Spirit formed in man is ſaid to be the <hi>candle of the Lord,</hi> uſeful there in ſearching the inner parts, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hearts ſecrets. This ſoul conſiſteth of reaſon, mind, will, and other faculties, fit to receive and retain God in its underſtanding and knowledge, without forgetting him, or being diſtracted by any Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or creaturely thing; and as the Reaſon is enlightned, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes clear, and bright, (free from errour and darkneſs) and the will and affections turned into the light and love of Chriſt Jeſus, (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed ſeed, and endleſs wiſdom of God) and is free from all beaſtly love of the fleſh, or any Creature, by his bleſſed love, meer mercy, and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign goodneſs of his holy Spirit.—The ſoul becomes as <hi>Adams</hi> was in Paradiſe, an innocent Life of converſing with God; and as <hi>Enochs,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:45573:11"/>that <hi>walked with God, pleaſed him, and was not found,</hi> &amp;c. But this ſoul cannot be found or known while man hath any thing moleſting it that is of his own body, or bodily wits, wherewith the ſenſes may be exerciſed, (<hi>ſo he that will ſave his liſe, muſt looſe it</hi>) for the reaſonable ſoul is a life immortal as well as inviſible, and hath a power and pure light of Chriſt in it ſelf, to ſee, know and love the truth, and true good, which is God onely: and he that truely feels and knows this, and is ſenſible of the touches thereof, feels and knows ſomewhat of the reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able ſoul, and the kindly workings of it; and the more he becomes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted therewith, (in this manner) the better he ſeeth and knoweth himſelf, and others alſo; and the more meek, humble, lowly, loving, tender and compaſſionate will he be towards all men and creatures.— And this was the higheſtate and condition, the heavenly and excellent dignity that <hi>Adam</hi> loſt when he became in love with himſelf, and ſelfiſh things, taking delight in earthly knowledge and worldly glory, whereby he fell into a dark, feeble and wretched eſtate, like the beaſt that periſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth; by which the love that before was clean, ſavory and ſweet in the holy Ghoſt, was ſo turned into a filthy beaſtly love and liking of himſelf and the creatures, wherein he ſought content, but found it not, (as it now is with all that remain in that degenerated nature;) and therefore the ſoul, to be brought back to know it ſelf, and be fitted for the ſervice whereunto it was ordained, by its being gathered up into its ſelf, and fully departed from beholding all creaturely things, or ſelfiſh uſe of bodily wits, arts, wiſdom or knowledge of man, (gotten by any natural means, ſtudy, labour, or exerciſe) ſo that the ſoul feel it ſelf in its own kind, in being as it were without a body; for as the eye of the ſoul is opened to Jeſus Chriſt in his pure light, and the love turned to him, it is received up above all bodily creatures, from beholding, liking, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, and uſing them; and ever diſdaining to be obedient to any worldly thought, or earthly thing, (that periſheth with the uſing) And while the ſoul is ſo kept, therein cometh no errour, nor deceit of its enemy, becauſe it then ſeeth Jeſus Chriſt above and in him, and holds the myſtery of faith in a pure conſcience, and all created things below under his feet, as not in him, nor of him. So <hi>David</hi> waited up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God for ſalvation, and his heart hearkned and indited of that good matter, and ſo became very ready in it, and ſaw the beauty of the Lord; and when the ſoul is brought into this heavenly harmony, it truly loves God, and all creatures ſpiritually, (not fleſhly and carnally as in its former ignorance) and is overcome with the ſweetneſs of Chriſts words of love, clearly revealed and ſpoken into the ear of the heart; which that ſoul heareth and obeyeth with good ſavour, and true joy in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; and ſo <hi>his ſecrets are with his ſaims;</hi> but not with the blind world; for the ignorant ſoul is ſo over-laid with worldly love, that it is all common as the high-way, ſo that every ſtirring of the fleſh and the Devil ſinketh into it, reſteth therein, and paſſeth through it as it pleaſeth without controule; and ſo if any good ſeed fall therein, it
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:45573:12"/>withereth for want of earth, it is choaked, or theſe fewls of the air ſteal it away, and devour it; there being onely the degenerate nature of old <hi>Adam,</hi> while that which became a living ſoul wants the quickning ſpirit to form the new man, ſettle and eſtabliſh the ſoul, not according to the carnal commandment, but after the power of the endleſs life. But how hard and difficult this is for the rude ſoul ſo unacquainted with it ſelf, and accuſtomed to receive tentations, make proviſion for the fleſh, and fulfil its luſts, and be ſtirring much in filth and fleſhly things, to enter this ſtrait gate to the knowledge of its ſelf, in its true light, is evident by the ignorance of moſt, and the ſmall numbers of thoſe that find it; for moſt men that would finde entrance, and know their ſouls, (in ſtead of turning in, into the light of Chriſt) turn their thoughts with imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations into their bodies, to ſeek for their ſouls, and to feel them; as though they were hid within their hearts, as their hearts are holden and hid within their bodies. Now if a man ſhould covet to know his ſoul, and that never ſo earneſtly, and ſeek for it in that manner in his body, he may not poſſibly ſo find it in its ſelf, but the more he ſeeketh to feel and know it by ſtudiouſneſs, (as he would know or learn tongues, arts, or other bodily things) the farther ſhall he be from it by that ſeeking; and therefore ſo many weary themſelves in vain, by ſeeking the door in a wrong way, and contrary nature, whereby it is hid from the wiſe and prudent, and revealed onely to babes and ſucklings at the breaſts of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation in the pure light of Chriſt, who is this Door, and by whom the diligent ſoul comes truely and quickly to enter, underſtand and know what its ſelf is with its true Teacher and Guide, while the other ſoul fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth ſuddenly into imaginations of bodily things and words; ſuppoſing thereby to have or gain the light of its ſelf, and ſo of God, and ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al things; which (as I ſaid before) can never be ſo attained, (by ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination or bodily wit) as the mind may ſee ſenſibly what is juſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween man and man by its underſtanding thereof; for then the ſoul might ſee it ſelf in underſtanding reaſonable things.—But the ſoul is to ſeek for a higher knowledge of, and in it ſelf, in the light, as to know that it is inviſible and immortal, of the breath of God, wherein God is to be ſeen ſpiritually, which is a great myſtery, not to be expreſt in words, but to be ſought out, and kept clean and bright from worldly wiſdom, fleſhly filth, and earthly vanities, above the ſenſual part, to ſee it ſelf in Jeſus Chriſt, the Way, Truth and Life; the ancient Path wherein the holy men of God ever walked to pleaſe him in diligent la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and travel of mind, and ſufferings of the outward man, and yet with fulneſs of joy and ſpiritual delight.</p>
            <p>In every ſpiritual work and employment, mans will, wiſdom, reaſoning and earthly affections, are to be left behind, as <hi>Abraham</hi> left his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants when he went to offer his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> for a burnt-offering to the Lord; and as <hi>Moſes</hi> drawing near to God put off his ſhoes, ſo all you
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45573:12"/>that will draw near unto the Lord God, caſt aſide, and leave behind you, your own ſelfiſhneſs, wills, wiſdoms, and imaginations, with every high thought that exalteth it ſelf, and keeps your ſouls from cloſing with the Lord in his holy ſervice, that you may be by him prepared to meditate, watch, pray, and give thanks in all things, and at all times, and embrace all divine counſel and heavenly help thereby, freely ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in the pure light and tender touches in the conſcience, to move the heart into an awful dread, and true fear of God, that by the ſtirrings of grace you may come to a knowledge of him ſpiritually; which gift is common to all, bat particularly received by the diligent ſoul that waits therein ſtable and firm, according as it ſo receiveth, and keepeth thereto with all ready chearfulneſs, moving in its own meaſure of grace ſo given, (though it be never ſo little) for the Lord is pleaſed ſuddenly to prepare mens hearts by putting meditations into their minds in the beginning and time of their converſions; eſpecially of ſuch as have been much occupied in worldly defilements; and then commonly the thoughts of ſuch (when once turned in) are moſt upon their ſins, with great ſorrow, meekneſs and tears, asking forgiveneſs, and watching thereto, as the Lord toucheth their ſo us ſharply to make them the ſooner clean; for then the ſin will be ever in the ſight as foul and horrible, and accompanied with fightings and hard conflicts in their conſciences, ſo as that they can take no reſt (until the Lord Jeſus give it as pleaſeth him) wherein is his tender mercy, that he may ſcowre and cleanſe ſuch ſouls the more ſpeedily, and forgive their ſins as he wipeth them away, (wherein juſtification is in ſanctification, and ſanctification accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with juſtification) and fitteth the ſoul to receive ſome ſpiritual grace and gift of his love; and ſo the holy Spirit oft ſtirreth to meditations in God, which worketh a kindly work in their ſouls to be waited in, and the fruits of the Spirit to be received, and all in Jeſus Chriſt, as the pure power, endleſs love and wiſdom of God that ſets the heart upon hungering after his vertue and ſpiritual diſcoveries, in ſuch exerciſes as God is graciouſly pleaſed to give in to the ſoul; and ſo meditation, watching and praying have no rules, bounds or limits ſet by man unto them, but when and as the Lord Jeſus pleaſeth to give by the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; for his gift it is, for diſpoſing of his choſen ones, and drawing in their ſouls to him, to be made wiſe in waiting, knowing and obeying him ſpiritually; wherein he giveth ſuch tender-heartedneſs, that they oft melt into devotion, and are raviſhed in ſouls above meaſure; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like as it ſometimes was with the Diſciples that ſate together, and were filled with the holy Ghoſt, and then ſpake forth the great and wonderful things of God, when all they knew was oy that ſpiritual raviſhing love; and ſo the Lord is pleaſed oftentimes to open his trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, and give to ſome very plentifally in all ages, as their ſouls come to be cleanſed, and the way made open and eaſie to them, though the doing thereof is a great myſtery to others that remain ignorant, or are net watchful and diligent; ſo that it paſſeth over them, (ſome growing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45573:13"/>contrary to it, and at enmity with it) for then the Lord withdraweth it again by reaſon of that ſlothfulneſs and abuſe, and ſometimes from the more diligent, to prove and try ſuch, that they may know wherein their ſtrength ſtandeth, and after that to feel their own weakneſs, and alſo know their reſpective ſtates, and how to love more ſpiritually: and ſo partly it was with the Diſciples that loved Chriſt much while in the fleſh with them, but then fleſhly as in his manhood; and therefore he told them it was neceſſary for them that he ſhould go away, and ſend the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt to teach them, to know and love more ſpiritually; and ſo the Lord oft withdraws himſelf outwardly, that the inward and heavenly preſence of his love may be the more earneſtly deſired, meditated on, and preſſed after; and that the ſoul may know its duty and employment in waiting, watching and ſuffering, until it be throughly renewed, ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and eſtabliſhed in his ſpiritual might and power, to glorifie him with more fervent love and holy worſhip: and if it ſo come to paſs, that he who is watchful and diligent therein, feels not this vertue enabling him to meditation, or ſpiritual imployment with his whole heart, (as he deſireth) but in ſtead thereof, fee leth many other thoughts run in upon him, and hinder him; and the more pain he taketh to keep his heart in watching and waiting for ſpiritual feeling, the farther off it is to the very laſt, and again harder afterwards: this is to teach him to watch more ſingly and ſincerely within the ſoul, and forget all things without; and to know that it is no eaſie thing to love with all the heart, until the heart be renewed; for this work will be found painful and laborious at firſt by the preſſing in of vain thoughts; and a full hard task it is for him that feels no grace, to be long meditating, waiting and watching in his ſoul; and much will he be encumbered with running and roving thoughts, as having gotten no ſure hold of his heart; and therefore is the heart to be kept unto God (in the light) with all diligence, for thereout come the iſſues of life or of death; for there is the good or the evil treaſure; and when well kept, there ſprings up wiſe and clear thoughts, clean affections, fiery deſires to ſpititual employment, vertue and vertuous actions: but otherwiſe thereout come the contrary, as evil thoughts, unclean deſires and affections; for every mans thoughts and meditations diſcover to him (that is of a heedful mind) what he is; as that whereon he thinketh and meditateth in, that he loveth, ſo that he loveth is his God; and the more he loveth God, the more he mindeth him, and meditateth on him, and his motions; and the more is the ſoul alive, and active to him, accounting it a ſhame to be fed with ſwines meat of fleſhly things and ſavours, wherein he feels no ſpiritual refreſhment, or true joy of love and delight.—And therefore he e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſets his heart and mind ſpiritually upon good, meditates on him, to know what he willeth, and to pleaſe him, ſee him, know him, have, love and enjoy him by his grace, and by degrees more and better; and as the ſoul ever keeps to theſe deſires, it will be ſhewed plainly (in the light) what is evil, and what good; what is pleaſing to God, and what
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45573:13"/>is contrary to him, and teach him all needful things for ſalvation, gain them for him, and beſtow them on him: and therefore as there is a ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faſt in this watchful deſire, victory will be given, ſo that the ſoul wait and meditate meekly and patiently until Jeſus Chriſt accept there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, give ſpiritual ſavour, and accompliſh his own work therein with vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory (as to other ſaints) in his own time, and ſo as it may become that ſouls chiefeſt joy to know and do that heavenly will, becauſe of the true ſpiritual delight therein.—But if man ſhould comply, and ſtrive with his bodily wits and worldly wiſdom, that will but drive him farther off:—and a wretched thing it is for any man to leave the inward watch and keeping of his heart, and ſhape to himſelf any outward form, figure, likeneſs or habit of vertue and holineſs in meditation, prayer, or other performance, to live in ſuch a form of outward exerciſe, beholding, joyning with, or imitating others, and ſuppoſing himſelf right and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous in ſo doing; for thereby he departeth from the light, guidance and government of Gods bleſſed Spirit, and deceiveth himſelf by think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he hath acceptance with God in his own doings; which ſo done, are directly againſt God, though they might be right and acceptable in thoſe that were led thereto by the Spirit of God.</p>
            <p>In this general calling of ſouls employment, nothing is rightly done but in watching and prayer; nor any true watch kept, or prayer pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, but in the light, and with a ſpiritual underſtanding, wherein vertue, wiſdom and ſtrength comes to be received and rightly employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: but this conſiſts not in learning to ſay words, or know how many parts prayer hath, or how to word it wiſely for the drawing of others af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and ſo to <hi>make long prayers for pretence,</hi> or as <hi>to be heard for much ſpeaking</hi> in the way that mans wiſdom teacheth of bodily exerciſe, (as did the Phariſees, whereof Chriſt warned his Diſciples) and lifting up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in their own ſtrength for the applauſe of men, that they may be reputed able Chriſtians, of excellent parts, full of knowledge, better then others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By which means many are themſelves deceived, by thinking they have the grace of Chriſt, and ſpiritual knowledge; and thereupon do ſo worſhip and pleaſe themſelves in their hearts, as if they were the onely men to pray, praiſe, and give thanks to God for, with, and above others, while all is but with their lips, vain words, and bodily wits, wherewith they onely diſhonour God, and defile themſelves and others, (that ſo joyn with them in words before their hearts and ſouls are therein agreed) by ſtealing the thanks, praiſe and worſhip from God to themſelves: like the Phariſees that would preſently be thanking God in words, and judging others, without the fear of God, faith in him, or any true love in feeling or affections, or deſires, to know their own hearts, and the iniquities thereof; much leſs that God (or others) ſhould know them, or they their duties to him.—But theſe forward minds are far from any ſure ſavour of delight, or being in God; and therefore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45573:14"/>their prayers or praiſes find no place with him, neither are they fair or ſeemly in the mouths of ſuch men where ſelf is loved, and their minds employed to provide for the outward man; and their pride is the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that ſo move, while they keep no true watch and guard over their thoughts, have no hold of their hearts, or ſtay of their minds, but multiply words in a powerleſs way of mans wiſdom, by imagining evils, finding faults, accuſing themſelves and others, and asking ſometimes what they do not in truth deſire, and oft what they do not want, but to ſpend upon their luſts; wherein the moſt are miſled, (as their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences witneſs) being ignorant of the A oſtles doctrine, fellowſhip and prayers, as they are of the knowledge of God, and the Godhead in the manhood of Chriſt — But that no man may miſtake my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding in the commands of Chriſt Jeſus my Lord, how to pray, or my practiſe in obedience thereto, let every one turn in their minds to his light, and there wait to know how he ſaid, <hi>Enter into thy cloſet, and ſhut thy door,</hi> (forget not that) <hi>and pray to thy Father in ſecret:</hi> So Chriſt himſelf prayed in the mountain, in the garden, in the deſart, alone from his Diſciples, and required th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m to <hi>watch and pray.</hi>—And alſo ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed joynt praying, and ſaid, Where two of you ſhall agree upon any thing to ask, it ſhall be granted of my Father which is in heaven: but (ſaid he) <hi>Uſe no vain repetitions, as the heathen do.</hi> And again, <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto have you asked nothing in my Name; ask, and you ſhall receive, that your joy may be full.</hi>—And his Diſciples did afterwards ſo ask in his Name, in faith and feeling, and that without wavering, (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) and prayed much, without ceaſing, with all manner of prayers and ſupplications in the Spirit, and with the Spirit and underſtanding, not knowing what to ask but as the Spirit helped, and made requeſts with ſighs and groans not to be uttered; and ſo asking, they received, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther privately alone, as <hi>Paul,</hi> when he felt the grace ſufficient for him; or as agreed in particular caſes, as was that in chuſing one in the room of <hi>Judas,</hi> their praying together with one accord, their ſitting ſo to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether waiting for the gift of the holy Ghoſt, (while they had received but the firſt fruits of the Spirit.) So likewiſe the Church prayed for <hi>Peter,</hi> and for others, on other occaſions; but ſtill more and more in the pure power and fervent love, as they received the more ſpiritual gifts of the holy Ghoſt.—By all which it is moſt evident, that the fire of that bleſſed Spirit of holineſs at all times kindled the ſacrifice; and the praiſe was not of men, but of God. And thus they prayed in Chriſts Name, as they were made partakers of his divine Nature: But what out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward naming of Chriſt was there in all this? (which is a work that the rude and un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly ſoul, the wild and worldly mind, knows nothing of:) Or what of ſet times, places, or perſonal reſpects was uſed therein? though now men have learned frequently to take the Name of God and Jeſus Chriſt in vain into their mouths, while they <hi>hate to be reformed,</hi> and neither know his Nature nor his Name; and therefore ſo many (under pretence of prayers and praiſes to God) ſtick not to ſcoft at the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45573:14"/>of the holy Spirit, gift of the holy Ghoſt, ſilent waitings upon God, watching, praying, new lights, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo go on blaſpheming the <hi>Father of lights,</hi> and the holy Name by which his ſaints are called, as things moſt contrary to their natures, and fleſhly affections; and therefore it highly concerns you every one to conſider well with what you come before the Lord, and to examine your ſelves whether you are in the faith, whether Chriſt Jeſus be in you, or you are reprobates. —Now if Jeſus Chriſt be forming in you, then the body is dayly dying; and if he be there formed, the body is dead becauſe of ſin, and the Spirit alive for righteouſneſs ſake; and then all ſenſible things of bodily wits, of imaginations, natural reaſon and underſtanding are brought under the true light and heavenly Spirit, and yeilded up, ſo as to know and do all in the Name of the Lord Jeſus; wherein I do not mean onely naming him, as his names are written in a Book, or on a Wall, or ſpoken of by polluted Livs,—but in the light, and by his Spirit, with the thoughts and affections, naked, bare, and free from beholding bodily or earthly things, as altered from fleſhly likings and affections into ſpiritual ſavour, ſweetneſs and delight in his divine pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, wherein the Spirit of prayer is freely given and felt, as a flaming deſire in the heart to Jeſus Chriſt, (the mighty power, love and wiſdom of God) by the heavenly touch of ſpiritual love, which is neither bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily, nor can be bodily felt; onely the ſoul that is wholly devoted to God may and doth feel it, but not with any bodily wit, wiſdom or skill, becauſe it is not felt but in the ſpiritual deſire of the ſoul that is clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed (or waiting to be cleanſed) from all unrighteouſneſs; and there it doth ſo warm, heat and quicken to watchfulneſs in prayer and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, that it enliveneth the ſoul, and raviſheth it more and more with pure joy and conſolation in him; ſo that the thoughts are gathered in at all times to think, ſpeak and act ſoberly, ſadly and ſeriouſly, and in prayer ever to expreſs ſuch words as God (onely by his Spirit) putteth into the heart, (like an eccho of mans voyce to his friend) which prayer is much alone, (as Chriſts alſo was) free from all lets and interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and is the gift of the holy Ghoſt, and laſteth not very long at a time, (in the fervour of it) for that it is laborious to the Spirit, though very pleaſant through the paſſion of love therein felt, truely taſted, and ſweetly ſavoured, (not much unlike that of <hi>Moſes</hi> when he opened not his lips, or of <hi>Hannah</hi> when ſhe did but move her lips) which breaketh down all luſts and likings of earthly things with ſo great force, as that the Kingdom of Heaven ſuffers violence thereby, while the ſoul is woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with the ſword of love, and thereby overcomes and obtains the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, in ſome ſenſe as <hi>Jacob</hi> did; but the body then ſeems to fall down, and may not bear it, becauſe the working is of ſo great force, that the moſt vicious and fleſhly man on earth, (ſo touched) would be right ſorrowful and ſad therewith for the time, and loath all his luſts and fleſhly likings of earthly things by him moſt delighted in before; as <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſaid the love and feeling of God was made as burning fire in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45573:15"/>his heart; and this is the holy Ghoſt and fire, even the love of God in man, burning and waſting all other loves and likings in mans ſoul, as a fire ſticking in the bones, and filling all the powers of the ſoul with grace and glorious ſweetneſs, as marrow fills the bones; and yet not without the wits, but within them; ſo full of might and power, (where it worketh within) that if ſmiteth down into, and through all; and throws down the body into quaking and trembling, for that it is ſo far unlike, and contrary to the body, that the body cannot skill of it, nor bear it: as was in like manner witneſſed in <hi>Moſes, David, Habakkuk,</hi> and others, and alſo in ſome of my dear friends that are living witneſſes thereof, (yet in the fleſh) onely our Lord Jeſus moderateth it, and tempereth it into a ſoft and ſober ſweetneſs, (by abating the fervour and motion in time convenient) and adminiſtreth life and peace as the ſoul becomes capable of it.—So that the holy Spirit teacheth for what and how to pray, watch, meditate and move to pleaſe, God without any mans teaching; and ſo our prayer is continual, without ceaſing, and moſt and beſt alone in the heart that is made pure and clean by the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration of the holy Spirit, that teacheth to do all things, and live ever in the love and ſweet preſence of God, without any great letting of luſts, vanities, or other tentations, as the ſoul becomes clean and purely devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to him.</p>
            <p>We read in holy Scriptures of the womans loſt Groat, the pearl and tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſure hid in the field, ſelling all, buying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly are matters of ſome importance to man, becauſe ſo ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantly expreſt by Jeſus Chriſt of himſelf and mans ſoul; as of light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a candle, ſweeping, ſearching, finding, rejoycing, digging deep, ſelling all other merchandize, buying, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore it skills much to have this Candle lighted, whereby mans ſoul may ſee this treaſure in its ſelf, and know the value of it, whereby it may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſell all for it; which may not be until it be known that it is loſt, and where, as in the inner part of mans own houſe: for as Jeſus Chriſt was loſt in mans ſoul, ſo there he is to be found;— what was loſt there by <hi>Adam,</hi> is to be found there in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, the pure pearl of high price, and primitive perfection: but he may not be there found in naming of him by any his outward names, nor as by faining his name, or any power in mans heart, by the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour of his minde, or ſtudying that name never ſo ſtrongly or ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly; for in this manner do thoſe that are far out of the way think to finde him, and by ſo ſeeking miſs of him, as neither knowing his Voyce, Name nor Nature; or taſte any ſavour of him, or ſee comelineſs in him to deſire him; but live without, as ſtrangers to him, (even without GOD in the world:) but he that comes to have an inward ſight of a little of that ſpiritual fairneſs and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which the reaſonable ſoul had of and in God at firſt, (that was
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45573:15"/>loſt in <hi>Adam</hi>) and is to be had again by grace in Chriſt Jeſus, as it ſhall be enlightned to ſee him ſpiritually, and ſhall not hide that light (as under a buſhel) by over-laying it with earthly buſineſs or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, but ſhall love it above all earthly things, even as the ſoul is ſwept with the fear of God, waſht with tears within, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſo the groat, the pearl, the Kingdom of heaven, (that Chriſt ſaid is within) the heritage of heavenly love is found and repoſſeſſed in mans ſoul; for it is not ſo eaſily found as many uſually ſuppoſe; nor is it a work of one day onely, but attained by much waiting in the light, ſweeping, ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, watching, praying, and ſilent mourning before the Lord; and as the heart and conſcience becomes purified, then he ſhall finde that homely and peaceable preſence of Jeſus Chriſt (the pearl of great price) in the glimmering ſhadow of pure ſhining brightneſs in his ſoul.— But though Jeſus Chriſt is ſo hid in the ſoul, yet no man is any whit the better thereby that doth not there finde him, and feel his operations ſpiritually, but remains (as it is written) a reprobate, whatſoever he may be otherwiſe.—And a great mercy it is to man that this Jewel was loſt where it may be found again by the light in the ſcarching and watchful ſoul, where Jeſus Chriſt full oft calleth and knocketh by his privy voice, ſtirring, reproving, and inviting the ſoul to a diligent ſearch, and withal to abandon other lovers, vanities and entangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that hinder the hearing of his voice; for (as it is ſaid) this daughter muſt conſider and forget her own people, and her fathers houſe, (of worldly thoughts, loves, cares and fears) which hinder the ſoul that it can neither ſee him, nor hear him; and therefore all troubleſome thoughts, reſtleſs noiſe and imaginations are to be put away, as <hi>Hagar</hi> the bond-woman, that may not be heir with the ſon of the free woman; for while the ſoul is in the bondage of corruption, there is nothing with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in but black clouds, and ſpiritual blindneſs, with fleſhly thoughts and deſires, crying againſt it in the dark conſcience: but as the inner eye of the ſoul is opened in the light which is of Jeſus Chriſt, (in whom dwells all the fulneſs of the Godhead bodily) there is that pure ſight and ſweet love of endleſs vertue and bleſſed reſt, which is found within the ſoul by the great and burning deſires for him, whereby all other loves and lovers are caſt out, and not ſuffered to reſt in the heart; which is a right ſeeking for him, this hid Treaſure.—And as this ſtirring and waiting in the light waxeth firm, ſtable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moveable, it will be holpen and comforted by inward and ſpiritual ſtrength of love and ſweet ſavour in the ſoul, with light of continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſpringing faithfulneſs, and aſſured knowledge of him, and the powers of the thoughts onely upon him, and freed from every other affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to reſt in the ſweet anointing, which is the ſhadow and taſte of Jeſus Chriſt; and the better any ſoul finds him, the more it will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him in cleanneſs of heart, and pureneſs of conſcience, to meet him more ſingly in the ſame way he appeareth, and wherein it hath ſeen and found him at firſt, (and other times ſince) moſt ſavourly. And though
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:45573:16"/>thou art altogether blind, and ſeeſt nothing rightly in thy ſelf, or of the Godhead of Chriſt; yet conſider ſeriouſly what thou wanteſt, and what thou haſt loſt; for thy ſoul can have no true content, or ſure ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, but in God from whence it is; and if thy heart ſay, I want, and would have Jeſus Chriſt, and nothing but him onely, wait therein for him, (as not ſatisfied with that appearance) and follow him as he leadeth thee, and more and more preſs forward to know him, and the power of his reſurrection, and fellowſhip of his ſufferings, and to be made conformable to his death, and ſo grow up in him, as he moves and grows in thee; and yet know that when thou haſt found the moſt of him in the higheſt raviſhments of ſpirit, (as <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Iohn</hi> in the mount, or as <hi>Paul</hi> mentioned) thou haſt not therein fully attained to him as he is in his joy, for he is ſtill above that any ſoul feeleth, as the fountain of all joy and ſweetneſs; but thou art ever to know and feel a ſpiritual long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after him, and a loathing of all things elſe; and then thou wilt find him more worth then all things, even then all viſions and revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, (though not without viſions and revelations) then all joy in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, if it might be had without him: for thou wilt then ſay in thy ſoul, (as <hi>David) whom have I in heaven but thee? and I deſire nothing in the earth beſides thee:</hi> as feeling and finding that his pure preſence onely gives underſtanding to the ſimple, he teacheth fools knowledge, whereat the Nations are angry, the people and their teachers rage, and imagine a vain thing againſt him and his holy One, as not willing to know him for fear of the Croſs and the ſhame, (which he deſpiſed for the joy ſet before him) and are therefore grieved that any others ſhould.</p>
            <p>Converſion is properly a turning from evil to good, from luſt to pure love, which is God; and this converſion is ever accompanied with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance from dead works that are paſt, and out of that nature, love and liking, wherein they were wrought, to ſerve the living and true God; and therefore it is not every turning of mans body and mind from one outward form or practice to another, as it were thereby to ſerve and worſhip God; for then the divers Political turnings of former and latter times, would be converſion to him; which he may not ſo accept, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he changeth not, but is the ſame at all times, even the unerring Father of ſpirits, and ſo to be worſhipped in ſpirit and in truth: and theſe are outward turnings from one act of mans will to another, or from evil to worſe; as the Proſelytes that the Phariſees made ſevenfold worſe then before, whilſt the ground of ſin, with its branches, remain ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, uncut down, or toucht, from whence ſuch traditional turnings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, to oppoſe that one truth and good way of the Lord wherein all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient ſouls are made free from ſuch ſhifts and changes: but while men have either not know the fear of the Lord, or are departed from it, left, and loſt the power of godlineſs, and ſimple truth in themſelves, (ſo
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45573:16"/>that their ſalt is without ſavour) their minds run abroad, and their hearts are filled with fleſhly deſires, loves and fears, wherein they labour night and day, to gain and keep the love and friendſhip of this world, (which is enmity to God) with the profits and pleaſures thereof, and therein ſerve themſelves, like the beaſts that periſh; and have their hearts oft filled with wrath and revenge, (like unreaſonable beaſts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others of their own kind) when they are hindred of any their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired ends, and likewiſe againſt ſuch as ſo hinder them not therein, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by ſtanding in their way, (as the Angel before <hi>Balaam</hi>) and ſo touching their more quick and tender parts, and that onely in love, to bring them back into the light and fear of the Lord, that their blind and dead ſouls might be lighted and enlivened to have regard to the honeſt principle of God in themſelves and others, that would rule all men ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right reaſon, and clear them of their fleſhly luſts that war a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their ſouls, did they not diſable themſelves thereto by withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it, and the checks thereof in their own conſciences, and by yeild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the enemy of their ſouls to have dominion over them, whereby the working of grace comes to be ſtopt, ſo that it may not enter, ſhine, finde room or reſt in their ſouls, though it be truely tendered, and there ſheweth it ſelf to diſcover things that differ, (as the Sun doth outward things where it is not letted) but while the ſtrong man thus armed keeps the houſe, the things he poſſeſſeth are in peace, the root, body and image of ſin ſtands, the falſe and miſruled love lives, and the ſoul remains in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſibly wrapt up in ſtinking rags of ſin and ſelfiſhneſs, where it feeds on nothing but black ſmoke in thick darkneſs, and ſpiritual blindneſs, as a body of ſin and death, born about, and heavily loading the ſoul and conſcience, that it cannot comprehend the light, but every tentation (of the ſame nature with it) prevails over it, and leads it captive more and more into a ſervile ſlavery and luſtful living in fleſhly filth; for ſin is not any corporeal thing, and therefore not corporeally to be deſtroyed, ſtriven about, or contended with, neither have men any power of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to amend this in themſelves, more then in others; and therefore cannot but ſo remain, until their minds be truely turned into, and ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly kept in the pure light, which onely can diſcover, and ſhew them the fairneſs or foulneſs of their ſouls, and the love of Jeſus Chriſt, therein giving power to take up and bear the croſs within (in the powers of the ſoul) and feel the two Laws warring againſt each other, (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times did) and the innermoſt (of the Law of the ſpirit of life) ſtriving for deliverance out of captivity, and to gain victory over the Law of the fleſh, earthly will, and worldly wiſdom that reſts ſeated in the bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wits; and as the reaſonable ſoul comes to take part with, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wait in the pure principle of light and ſpiritual leading, to have ſome ſight of it ſelf, and ſomewhat of the treaſures of wiſdom and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge that are in Chriſt Jeſus, (as his free gift to all obedient ſouls) thereby the ſoul begins to ſee ſomewhat of it ſelf, and how highly it is concerned to keep a conſtant inward watch, labour and ſtrive (by the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45573:17"/>meaſure of light and life (ſo in wardly received) to keep the thoughts from all bodily things, until the ſore pain and miſerable blindeneſs of that condition (as <hi>Paul</hi> when he cried out, <hi>O wretched man that I am!</hi>) be found and felt, and then will the Lord Jeſus appear as the pain of this dark ſoul and conſcience; wherein is to be a free ſuffering, with a pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent waiting and abiding with him (in his love and meekneſs) until he ſhall pleaſe to raiſe the ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l up, and cauſe the light to ſhine out of, and over this darkneſs, as the day-ſtar ariſing in the heart, to give another life, whereby to overlive all the former dead and dark life, and then to think no more on that darkneſs paſt, (as a woman forgets her pain and peril, for joy that a man is born:) loathe and deſpiſe it; but be ever ready and quick in keeping the heart, and taking heed that no open door nor privy hole, be left to imaginations, wiſdom of words, or earthly va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, that would draw out the ſoul from the love of God; ever mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that as we have born the ugly image of the earthly, ſo it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that we bear the image of the heavenly; and as our Lord Jeſus breaks down this earthly image of falſe love and likings, he ſets up the contrary vertues of pure love, meekneſs, patience, and brotherly kinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, of his own forming, in the poverty of ſuch ſpirits; and alſo gives true zeal in ſpiritual devotion, with ſoberneſs and chaſtity in ſoul and body; and ſo puts down the old man, with his deeds, rotten deſires, and affections, and there ſets up the new man of a meek and chaſte ſpirit, (created in him to good works, to walk therein) with all his parts and members fitly compoſed together for his ſervice and glory; wherein the old members, eye, ear, heart, affections, imaginations, or deſires, will not ſerve the turn; but all the whole veſſel muſt be new, to hold the new wine and heavenly liquor of the bleſſed and endleſs life, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be freed from fleſhly uſes, vain thoughts, light looks, unſavory words, carnal reaſonings, and heeding the praiſe or diſpraiſe of men, and mens judgements; but ſurmounting and over-topping all lets and impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments in the way of this perfect freedom, and lightſome liberty in the Lords ſervice, as guided and ſtrengthened therein by his holy Spirit, as it turns the reaſon into that pure light, and the will into the eternal will, which is a great work, and therefore to be well waited in until there be no ſin charged or felt as a load on the conſcience, but all freely pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (as it is diſcovered to the ſoul) and clean wiped away, and ſo the ſoul reformed by the ſiritual light, and bright beams of Jeſus Chriſt, (let into it) as burning deſires, clean affections, holy and wiſe thoughts and conſiderations, and therewith abilities to flee all deadly ſtirrings in this travel of ſoul from the firſt old <hi>Adam</hi> to the ſecond, that makes all things new.—And though men ſhould otherwiſe ceaſe to med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle with worldly buſineſs, avoid outward delights and pleaſures, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote themſelves to pray, read, ſtudy, learn and confer of heavenly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; ſigh, weep, or do any other act outwardly, or otherwiſe; yet if he love himſelf, mind or carefully heed providing for the fleſh, or outward man, or have any other earthly fears, cares, or immoderate deſires; this
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45573:17"/>will not do it; but the greater is the deceit, by ſuch forſakings and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, in his becoming affected with himſelf, as if better then others; or in ſlighting others, by terms or titles of diſtinction, (whereby he is ſo much the worſe, and more diſabled to good:) or if he ſuffer his heart (at all) to reſt in bodily feelings of ſpiritual comforts or ſweetneſs, or ſet his heart on any ſuch fleſhly ſavours; he thereby loſeth that life he ſeemeth to ſeek for, becauſe not rooted and grounded in love; but the fleſhly part gains ground again, in the earthly dark and dead nature; and then is the law of ſin ſerved for the time: but yet if there be no wilful ſin, or liking thereto, it is not he, but ſin that ſtirreth in him, which he conſenteth not to: And thus have many been troubled and overlaid for a time with weight upon their weaker parts, that they have not had (for that time) any clear ſight, or freedom in themſelves, but ſate ſadly without any knowledge of their own conditions, or abilities to move one ſtep forward, becauſe ſin got ſo great a hold (or as a lodging) in their fleſhly parts, that it troubled the Reaſon, and ſometimes ſo far prevailed, as to occupie the affections of the ſoul, while the Spirit as a law within, was labouring for deliverance, until the Lord Jeſus pleaſed to prepare the ſoul, and break into it by his bleſſed preſence, and give it feeling of pure love; and ſo ſtretch the heart forward, to fathom and follow what is before; for behinde are all bodily things, thoughts, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, fears, and ſuch like, that hinder the comfort in, and ſpeed of, the whole work: for nothing is to be kept from the ſlaughter, that is for deſtruction; no mean in deſtroying ſin, though a right hand or eye, they muſt away, and give place to the divine work of the Spirit in the light, which is b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore; as the ſpiritual vertues beg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n in the Reaſon of the willing ſoul, and to be perfected in love, as it comes to be reformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the grace of Chriſt, to a perfect hatred of the deeds of the fleſh, and all wavering mindedneſs, and want of love; for otherwiſe he hinders the work through his own w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lfulneſs, and choice, in the contrary nature; which will cauſe all to be to little purpoſe, troubleſom, and heavie, as a working in the fire, (if not thereby deſtroyed) becauſe of his not feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any grace, or ſpiritual ſavour therein.</p>
            <p>The ways, wiles and d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vices of the evil one, to deceive and devour ſouls, are ſuch, and ſo divers, (in theſe later days) that the ignorant and unskilful ſouls, may not eaſily eſcape, becauſe he takes all advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, by the times, temptations, bodily wits, and faculties of ſuch dark ſouls, to lead them into ſelf-love, and the ſundry kindes of luſtful living, in the vanities of their mindes, wantonneſs and pleaſure, upon the earth, (as <hi>fitting themſelves for a day of ſlaughter</hi>) and ſo keeps them (while he may) in preſumption, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but if once he ſee any ſoul would entirely give themſelves to be ſpiritually employed, then he ſtriveth (by himſelf and his miniſters) to ſet their ſins in order before them, and tells them they are great ſinn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs, and more in this change and turning then in any
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45573:18"/>thing before, ſaying to them, That is not the way, but a denial of Chriſt, a fancie, and frenzie, of a Fanatick ſpirit, and for ſome wicked end; and that it will bring them into contempt, want and poverty, wherein none will pity them: that they muſt change their conditions with their mindes, wives and children come to want: that they will fall into bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly ſickneſs, and be laid in priſons: that they ſhould have learned men to adviſe them better, the Miniſters to admoniſh them, and pray for them: to take counſel at <hi>the Prieſts lips,</hi> which <hi>preſerve knowledge;</hi> and not run of their own heads, with a few giddy, contemptible people, that are ignorant of the Scriptures, and Original tongues: and if they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part not from their new way, greater temptations will overtake them. And with much more of this kinde, doth this flattering devil ſeek to beguile ſuch ſouls as hearken to him, by the <hi>cunning craftineſs</hi> of ſuch as <hi>lie in wait to deceive,</hi> and that entangle <hi>with enticing words of mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom,</hi> to beguile their ſouls, with bodily ſavours, ſweetneſs of wits, arts, and outward exerciſes, and thereby (if poſſible) draw them aſide from the ſimplicity, and puff them up with conceit of themſelves; as if they had by ſuch wiſdom (and the ways thereof) formerly found the feeling of heavenly joy; and ſo lead them back again, and up into high no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and conceits of a proud minde; until they become baſe and block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh, and thereby fall full lowe at laſt, with their cold, dry and barren ſouls: for the more they imagine to gain by ſuch means, the greater will be their loſs, and they the farther off from what they ſo ſeem to ſeek, and much more indiſpoſed to return into the right way of obtaining it; for thereby the minde will be oft, and highly lifted up, as if it were in a happie eſtate and condition, more holy, vertuous, and better then others; and to rejoyce, as if they had eſcaped a very great temptation; and to conceive angry ſtirrings in themſelves, when others ſeem not ſo to eſteem of them: and the flattering ſpirits will ſuddenly praiſe and applaud ſuch, as for good deeds, and vertuous living; and this laſt is the ſoreſt and greateſt of all temptations, and moſt dangerous, becauſe of the delight men will ſeem to feel about them, by ſuch ſounds to the ear, and ſweet ſavour of ſenſe, tickling them with delight therein; as if all were well, and they had much grace, and were rightly travelling, with their mindes from fleſhly things, while they are onely raviſhed with ſpiritual pride, wherein the vain love, and ſelf-conceit, prayeth, weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſpeaketh and thanketh God, (with the Phariſee) while they know not God; but their proud hearts deceive them, and lead them to ſhew outward love and meekneſs in ſpeech and geſture, as if they were ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually vertuous, and that they diſliked nothing but ſin, onely becauſe it is contrary to God; and yet are even then at the gate of ſpiritual death, ſo puft up with pride and pleaſure therein, as that they are even dead while they live, or rather twice dead, and pluckt up the roots; become ſervants to men and times, miſtaking one thing for another, with their fleſhly hearts got aloft, and puffed up, reſting in the root and rottenneſs of ſin, black and thick darkneſs, filling their ſouls; which may be hid
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45573:18"/>from ſome men, yet Chriſt Jeſus ſees it, and abhors it and their ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, becauſe of their hypocriſie and hereſie, ſo accompanied with bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſpiritual pride, (which was never learned of Chriſt) as their God; for man maketh any thing his God that his heart is in love with; that he takes content in, dares ſin againſt God for, or wrong any man by; and ſo ſuch men have their divers kinds of Idol-gods; one his bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, another the applauſe of men; a third his opinions and words, heard or ſpoken, (wherein ſuch ſerve not the Lord Jeſus, but their own luſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mindes) and every other thing that a man chuſeth by his own act, to take pleaſure in, is his God; and then when God ſtirs up ſuch ſouls to obedience, and gives them ſuitable abilities, theſe proud hearts reſiſt all, and in ſtead of obedience, become rebellious, heady, harſh, and high-minded, abuſing the tender mercies of the Lord God, in the light of his ſpiritual leadings to repentance: and this condition is (as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid) the more deſperate, becauſe therein ſuch conclude that all is well, and ſound, and that they are right, ſure, and righteous, (even above any ordinary Phariſee) and ſo arrogate to themſelves. And therefore hear and conſider, thou that thinkeſt thou ſtandeſt, that ſuppoſeſt thou art raiſed from death to life, haſt taſted of the good word of God, and born (it may be) ſome afflictions; and take heed of this falſe liberty, for then will Satan try and winnow thee, and be teaching thee, as aforeſaid; or as ſometime he would have done Jeſus Chriſt, to caſt himſelf down, to turn ſtones into bread, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And full many have ſo fallen by his means into this high ſpiritual pride, and thought that therein they have done God ſervice; and unleſs the ſoul be rooted and grounded in love, and ſo in meekneſs, (with a ſpiritual feeling of Jeſus Chriſt as God equal with the Father) it will be apt to yeild to ſuch transformings, and to ask (as the Diſciples ſometimes did) <hi>who ſhall be greateſt?</hi> and ſo may ſoon depart from the ſimple and pure life, and looſe their hold of that which leads the humble and meek to perfection: and therefore what great care, waiting and diligence; yea, what faithfulneſs is requiſite in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the light that will let men ſee the deceit, and lead them in the way to eſcape the evil thereof? for (as we read) the Lord Jeſus was tempted, but was not overcome, becauſe the Devil found nothing in him whereto he might faſten the temptation.—And this is of experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and adviſement to all willing ſouls, that when tentations come, and move to fleſhly love and likings of earthly things, heed them not, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider them not, whether it concern outward profit or loſs, ſcorning or deſpiſing, frowning or flattering; for if the Devil (by himſelf or means of his inſtruments) prevail with thee to conſider it, thou art then (there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by) more then half overcome, becauſe the ſame nature in thee will be apt to joyn with it; and the great danger is, leſt thou ſhouldſt like it, or be afraid of it, and ſo be overcome by it.—Therefore keep with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, in the light, that thou maiſt be able to ſay to thy ſelf, (in that caſe) I have choſen my way, my part, my portion is in Chriſt Jeſus; him I love, in him I have righteouſneſs and ſtrength, in him I rejoyce and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45573:19"/>enjoy all things; and nothing will I have out of him, for he accepts me as worthy to love him, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and be ſure to be bold and clear there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and then ſhalt thou find thine enemies leſs bold againſt thee; for truth never ſuffers more than when it is coldly and faintly owned.—Though theſe enemies will be ſtill ſtriving againſt thee, and telling thee of dangers, and perilous things to befal thee in that way, and ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to hinder thee by ſlanders and reproaches of all kindes, ſtri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> thee of thy reputation, and ſtrive to drive thee aſide into anger, and words of reb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke, that they may have whereof to accuſe thee: therefore take h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed thereof, and <hi>keep thy tongue as with a</hi> bit and <hi>bridle;</hi> and as thou com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt to know Jeſus Chriſt ſpiritually, thou wilt alſo come to a hearty love, in being deſpiſed, ſputned at, trampled upon, and abuſed; and if there ſhall happen to be ſome inward regret, or riſing againſt it, the light will ſhew thee the evil of it, and the ſpirit of love will ſuppreſs it, and give victory over it; and (as thou attendeſt faithfully) thou wilt find and know, that God forſaketh no man, in ſuch tentations, unleſs it ſhall be to encreaſe their ſpiritual ſtrength, (if they ſuffer a while patiently, and not turn to folly) that they may find Jeſus Chriſt, the ſweet and ready way, full of ſpiritual refreſhments and comforts; and themſelves poor, blind and naked without him, and to have nothing b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t what he giveth, and herein ſuffer much buffeting of Satan and his miniſters, witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t heeding, or rather with deſpiſing ſuch tentations, ſetting them at nought, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But if any ſhall ſtrive with his thoughts and bodi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y wits to drive away tentations, and put them out as by maſtery, thereby will the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my get advantage and overcome: and therefore (as before, ſo I ſay a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) ever withdraw thy thoughts from the tentations into the light of Jeſus Chriſt, where the ſtriving and life of ſtrength lieth, and wait on him for deliverance and victory.—And alſo beware thou never ſhew ſuch temptations to any worldly men (though reputed never ſo wiſe, learned or religious) that have not felt the like tryals in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, for they will certainly bring thy ſoul into greater danger by their worldly advice to thy fleſhly feeling.—And this alſo know, that the Lord is pleaſed to leave the ſoul, ſo ſometimes (for its tryal a little ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) that in mercy he may gather it more cleanly into himſelf, to grow and ſpring up as a morning-ſtar; and deliverance he will ſurely give (in the needful time) to all his members, that they may truſt in him more fully; and then he gladdeth them with his preſence, and faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to himſelf; ſhewing them his ſecrets, and giving them trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of wiſdom and knowledge: He brings in light, and expels darkneſs; opens the eye of the ſoul, and lighteth it to ſee how good it was for it to be ſo troubled: the like whereof <hi>David</hi> witneſſed, and thereby learned the Lords righteous judgements.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here ſay little of the Faith that ſtands in the wiſdom of men, (though that be moſt in uſe and eſteem with the worldly wiſe men of this
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:45573:19"/>generation) becauſe it is of mentioned in other places as the great En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of deceit, ſerving to ſilence the voice of Chriſt in their own and others conſciences, and for other earthly ends, and to lead them into pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous paths of ſin and ſelfiſhneſs, from the pure and ſpiritual path of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the endleſs light, love, wiſdom and power of God, whereby mans converſion is hindred, and the way thereto, as it were (thereby) blockt up; for in mans converſion, before reaſon be turned into light, and will into love, and the ſoul comes into a waiting condition for clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, it uſually feels its ſelf heavy loaden, d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll, and indiſpoſed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by reaſon of ſuch obſtructions as thereby (and otherwiſe alſo) lie in the way: yet as Jeſus Chriſt moveth and deſireth, ſo is he therein covertly deſired; and thereupon he f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rther moveth to work his ſecret work in man, as in a reaſonable inſtrument, that by degrees may have faith wrought in him, with knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, and his ſpiritual pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, light and truth; and for that end, that ſo I begins to wait upon him at all times diligently with the whole heart, until he give words whereby to pray, and do fitly order the affections to that contin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>al du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, without uſing words otherwiſe heard, leſt vanity of mind and ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual enemies enter and blind the eyes, and hinder the ſoul from chaſing the love of God in Chriſt Jeſus, whereby the heart ſhould be cleanſed and eſtabliſhed to feel and find how fair and profitable his work will be in and to the ſoul, as it comes to know the two days or lights, the falſe light and true light, the love of this world and fleſhly things, and the pure love of Jeſus Chriſt, through grace eſtabliſhing the ſoul, with the real difference between them, and begins to feel ſome increaſing know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in the true light; to feel the falſe light, worldly love, and luſtful pleaſures ſeem l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ttle, and paſs away as a ſhadow; which is the light that the Devil brought in by <hi>Eve</hi> and <hi>Adam,</hi> ſaying, they ſhould <hi>be as gods knowing good and evil;</hi> whereby the inner eye of <hi>Adams</hi> ſoul was ſhut, and the ſpiritual light then over-laid, as withdrawn from his ſoul, and the outward eye of fleſhly love and worldly liking was opened in him, with which he did not ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e before, nor know that new day of evil and darkneſs, wherein he afterwards, and all his poſterity, (in that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) now rejoyce, and take their paſtime; and yet, but as in vain ſhews, unskilful heavineſs of heart, with fleſhly angerineſs, fears and dreads; and this before the eye of mans underſtanding be opened, ſo as to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern ſpiritual things, or to underſtand Scriptures; and no doubt but theſe are well known unto many, who have alſo in prayer and otherwiſe felt and taſted the ſweetneſs of the ſpiritual work, ſo as to have thought nothing ſo pleaſing as it, and have not known what it was that they ſo delighted in, but it was indeed the gift of God in the light, to be waited on as it begets devotion, contrition, many ſweet tears, burning deſires and mournings for ſin, to ſcowre and cleanſe the heart, and mould it into a wonderful ſweetneſs of a ready mind to fulfil the will of God, and to truſt him without queſtioning what ſhall become of the outward man, or other like relations, ſo as the will of the Lord were done in him and by
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45573:20"/>him. But ſome that ſo obtained to this firſt gift of God in light, that would have wrought them into a like condition and reſolution, (had he been attended upon therein) have departed from it, as many did that followed Chriſt, (for a time) which cauſed him to ſay to <hi>Peter</hi> and the reſt, <hi>Will ye go away alſo?</hi> but if ſuch inward feeling as this, bring with it true and pure love, then it may not be ſo loſt, though ſloth may cauſe it to ſeem hid or clouded for a time, and eſpecially in caſe the mind ſo moved ſhall turn out (by conſent) into the viſible things, and thereupon the evil one catch it, and transform it into an angel of light; and then that ſoul is not able to ſee clearly within it ſelf who is working there, (much leſs afar off) though he have a kind of outward feeling, but no ſtability of ſoul, or inward certainty, but all ſounds and favours, any way ſatisfying the ſenſes, draw out the minde from Jeſus Chriſt, the true light, ſo that it cannot then come to ſee and behold him ſpirituaſly, and love him perfectly, as leading into heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thoughts and deſires, and to a loathing of ſelf and all earthly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights; and then (by reaſon of ſuch lazie and luſtful deſires) the ſtead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſt minding of JESUS is neglected, and the intended knot of union (then in knitting) becomes looſe, and unties for the time. — But of this be ſure, that what ſpiritual feeling, revelation or manifeſtation knits that knot of love and devotion to Jeſus Chriſt, and opens the eye of the ſoul to a more clear and ſpiritual knowing of him, alſo begets meekneſs, and love, and ſettledneſs in the ſoul, and caſts man down by reaſon of his unworthineſs and unprofitableneſs towards God and man, as a wretch and out-caſt of men, unmeet to live amongſt them, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his beaſtly, lewd, fleſhly and blind mind, ignorant of ſpiritual things, and of his own ſoul, not knowing Jeſus Chriſt, nor any of his ſpiritual workings or worſhip; for that none worſhip him truely, but in the ſpiritual revelation and feeling of himſelf: for it is by meekneſs of love that a man is kept ſingle to God, and free from harſhly beholding other mens deeds, (unskilfully done) and looking on others evil acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons irregularly, or otherwiſe then as matters of mourning and cautions to himſelf and them; and if he reprove them, to do it in love ſoberly and ſecretly, and to look on God and on himſelf as if there were no other man in the world, and himſelf moſt wretched and vile; and teacheth him ever to watch diligently, leſt ſin get entrance into his ſoul; to judge or condemn no man haſtily, but ſay always to himſelf, <hi>What have I been? what am I? what hath God done for me? what have I done againſt him, and what for him?</hi> thereby to come and ſee his own ſtate and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and as the Lord giveth him grace, to wait in that his own mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the gift, and never fain to have more then he hath in faith and feeling, or act otherwiſe then he hath received grace, and keeps to that; (though it be never ſo little) and moves not our of that ſo received, or to do any thing becauſe another did or doth it, for that cannot be of faith, but will run a man out of breath, and become ſin to his ſoul.— And know for certain, that he who waiteth meekly, and acteth according
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45573:20"/>to his meaſure of grace received, until more be given by the pure mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, and yet ever deſireth more, moſt and beſt, (but works onely according to what he hath) ſhall be ſure (in due time) to have a ſuitable ſupply. And thus ought every man to enter particularly into his own ſoul, to know it, and the ſtrength there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, with its fairneſs or foulneſs; to ſee its dignity at firſt, and wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by ſin ſince, with the labouring in the ſoul againſt the ground of all ſin, (little and much) which ground is onely the falſe miſruled love of mans heart to himſelf, from which at firſt ſin had its beginning in him; and until this fallow-ground be plainly plowed up, and all fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and worldly loves, hopes, deſires and fears be removed, the ſoul can never ſee and feel the pure burning ſpiritual love of Jeſus Chriſt, nor enjoy his preſence in the ſoul, or diſcern ſpiritual things by the light of underſtanding; (which is not right until wrought into the fear of God) for thereby is the mind and heart drawn out to all ſinful likings; by mans own underſtanding to reſt in all beaſtly love, earthly thoughts, and fleſhly things; and therefore it is (at firſt) ſo laborious to love Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt truely and ſpiritually, and may not be while his love is not felt therein, becauſe that muſt teach him to hate his fleſhly life, father and mother, (as Chriſt ſaid) and take up the croſs quietly, and follow Chriſt, (as before is ſaid) to the mortifying of his members that are earthly, even every unclean luſt, and unskilful love of himſelf, and ſee the ground of ſin broken within, and by degrees the body thereof de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as there ſhall be a loathing and deſpiſing of it in the heart, and of all the beauty, liking and fairneſs of this preſent world, as a ſtinking Carrion; labouring night and day to war ſpiritually againſt it, and all its enticements, as the ſpiritual eye ſhall be opened, for otherwiſe none can ſee it, much leſs war againſt its enterpriſes.</p>
            <p>As <hi>Adam</hi> by his ſin ſaw and felt the new light of fleſhly love and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings of this world, (which in his innocency he ſaw not) in the new and evil day that <hi>Job</hi> curſed, (being the concupiſcence which the Devil and man made) might periſh, and be no more: —for the everlaſting love of God in Jeſus Chriſt, is the true light and bleſſed day, (love and light being of and in him) in whoſe light the children of the day ſee light, and greatly rejoyce. But they that truely ſeek him, muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to abide a while in the darkneſs, for the darkneſs was before the light, <hi>and the evening and morning were the firſt day;</hi> and man may not ſuddenly come from the dark day, (which is the love of himſelf and this world) into the perfect love of God in and to his ſoul, and to ſee and feel ſpiritual things, gaining victory in his thoughts to bring all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to obedience; becauſe it is firſt night or darkneſs with him, wherein the love of this world is ſhut out, and the day ſprings from on high, and viſiteth; and as the ſoul becomes quiet and ſtill, the light breaks forth more and more unto the perfect day, as he becomes wholly acquitted of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45573:21"/>his ſin, and the favour of it.—But as there is a paſſing to this light through the evil day or night of darkneſs, (wherein is no pleaſure, but ſorrow and ſighing, doubts and deadneſs of ſoul) there is a blind long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, and thinking on Jeſus Chriſt, how good and bleſſed he is, with deſires to feel his love, and be lighted with his preſence, (as <hi>David</hi> ſought God in the night) to be hid (though in pain) from beholding the world, and its falſe likeneſſes, (which ſo well pleaſe thoſe that are blind in ſpiritual things) and dwell quietly in this darkneſs, (wherein Satan cometh with his likeneſſes and light, under colour of true light) until the light of love (by little and little) break forth to him (ſo dwelling in the ſhadow of death) and ſhine through the darkneſs and death, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for there are many that would ſeem to forſake the love of the world, and alſo would come to the love of God, and his light, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand him: but through this darkneſs they will not come to know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves what they have been, and are in their ſinfulneſs againſt God, to enter into themſelves, and view all things there, with all wicked ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings and riſings in their hearts of pride, envy, anger, and other evils, and to wait deſiring in the ſtill ſilence, and ſpiritual watchfulneſs to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, (as his Saints ever did) but ſo ſoon as (in their own wills) they ſeem to have forſaken the world outwardly, they preſently think themſelves holy, and full fit for ſpiritual underſtanding, and heavenly myſteries; and that they love God perfectly, and have received grace through the ſpecial gift of the holy Ghoſt; for they are ſtirred and ſeem to feel knowledge, as it were then given to them, without great ſtudy before-hand, and a hear of deſire therewith to preach forth truth and righteouſneſs, and will run into words thereof as with great for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardneſs and zeal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And this they hold for the grace of God, and viſitation of his bleſſed light, before their ſouls paſs through this dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: — though this light of knowledge, and heat of deſire, they feel, cometh not of the true love of Jeſus Chriſt, but from the Devil, and his transformings, as being onely a fained light, and likeneſs of the true light, and Son of God; whereby cunningly he leadeth blind ſouls into a preſuming of being themſelves righteous, and abuſing others, (as the Phariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es did) and ſo have no light of grace to them given by the holy Ghoſt: for though the knowledge they have were in it ſelf outwardly true, yet by the Devil and mans own wit, it makes onely a fained light of true things, but not the light of the true Son, nor approved of by his pure light in their Conſciences; and ſuch men are ſo blind by theſe fained lyes, and puffed up with ſpiritual pride, that they ſee it not, nor are willing to conſider it; but highten their hearts againſt the true light, ſurpoſing the feeling in their own wills is perfect freedom of ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit; and ſo like clouds without rain, (toſſed to and fro) bring forth one device, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rour and hereſie after another, which are known by their wild minds exerciſed in covetouſneſaid) this wiſs;s, much vanity, talking, diſputing, contending about words, rayling and reviling others, and perfecuting them; and yet will not be aſhamed to ſay, They do all this in charity,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45573:21"/>and zeal for righteouſneſs.—But (as <hi>James</hi> ſaid) this wiſdom is not from above, but is <hi>earthly, ſenſual and deviliſh:</hi> and therefore this cunning (that brings forth ſuch Saints) is not of <hi>the God of peace,</hi> and <hi>Father of lights, (with whom is no variableneſs, or evil ſpeaking)</hi> but ſuch as Jeſus Chriſt uſed not, nor allowed in his Diſciples; but to do all in his ſpiritual light, and faith in him, which is a myſtery held in a pure Conſcience, in the love and meekneſs of Chriſt Jeſus: for it is the fire of love that goeth before him, to conſume the enmity and evil works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereof ſuch are ignorant as have not been ſmitten down from their height and haughtineſs into the loweſt degree of meekneſs, and there purged from all ſpiritual filthineſs; without which they cannot endure the bright ſhining of ſpiritual light, the precious liquor of the love of Jeſus Chriſt, becauſe not purified in the heavenly furnace, to receive the gracious light of heavenly knowledge and perfect love, which is the true <hi>Son of rightcouſaeſs, (with healing under his wings)</hi> and he that thereby reforms in feeling, through the dear light that ſpringeth forth, and ariſeth after this darkneſs, which is not well known but to the ſoul that travelleth in darkneſs, and cryeth after light, to ſhew it the right way, and comfort it in travel therethrough: for after true dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, where one firmly ſets himſelf to forſake the love of this world, and through grace come to a feeling and knowing of himſelf, and keeps meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs therein, he may not be deſtroyed by errours or fancies; for the feeling of grace in that meek darkneſs, teacheth the ſoul to be faithful, and watchful againſt the enemies motions, and ſubtil ſlights. — And it may ſo be, (and oft is) that ſome have theſe workings, and firm deſires in them, and yet remain doubtful thereof what the iſſue may be; but ſuch (as they know it begets love and meekneſs) are to keep it ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly, and purſue it fervently, that no creature hinder it: for this grace will ever be free from ſin, and worldly buſineſs that hinders it; which cannot be, until he be throughly dead to the world, poor inward and outward, and have fully forſaken the love of it, without any worldly cunning, covering or device, whereby to be eſteemed above others; but rather deſpiſed of the world, and all worldly men; ſets not his heart upon his own deeds or vertues, nor loves nor allows any heart-riſings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt others for any matter or cauſe whatſoever:—ſo that he doth not diſeaſe, nor anger any man willingly in word or deed, nor pats any truſt in worldly goods or friends: —for otherwiſe he cannot be free to wait on Jeſus Chriſt as he ought; for ſo long as love to any creature or luſtful deſire carries the mind out from Jeſus Chriſt, (his true light within) he cannot die to the world, nor come into this darkneſs of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, &amp; be crucified to the world, as not deſiring it, nor accepting it.—And for this forſaking, (ſaid Jeſus Chriſt) he ſhall have a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold, even the profit of this darkneſs, be hid (through grace) from worldly goods, that he ſeek them not earneſtly, is not letted by them, loveth them not, looketh not after them; and therefore hath an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fold more then any King, or rich man of the earth, that takes care
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45573:22"/>to keep that he hath, and yet covets more; for he that coveteth Jeſus Chriſt, and him onely, he hath more reſt of heart and conſcience, true love and delight in his ſoul, in one hour, then he that loveth the things of this world, hath, or can have, in all his life-time: and this darkneſs is but as mid-day, when the Sun ſhineth out of the darkneſs, and Jeſus Chriſt giveth reſt to his beloved, that ſtandeth firm in his counſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, and doubteth not, nor is afraid for any evil tydings, becauſe his heart is ſined; and is well aſſured, that the light of knowledge, and fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of ſpiritual love, is in Chriſt Jeſus, of him, and for him; and that the darkineſs in forſaking of worldly love, is by his forming, and reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the ſoul onely to and for himſelf; and that he reformeth us, in us, and not without us; for grace is inwardly given at firſt, and ſo wrought by degrees as man applyeth his heart thereto. As firſt, Jeſus Chriſt by his light and Spirit calleth from worldly vanities, and that then brings great ſweerneſs, and joy with it: but if left, and not ſeconded, it ſtayeth there but for a little ſeaſon, though the remembrance thereof abideth; and after that, the time of reforming and ſetting the ſoul at rights, is with much labour and watching; for when the mind is ſet againſt all ſin within and without, and the deſire wholly on the love of Jeſus Chriſt, wherein there will be felt many lets, (from within, in his own will, and without from his enemies by temptations) and his great tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he hath lived ſo long in, the falſe love of the world; and this will ſtick cloſe to him, until he paſs through ſpiritual tribulation, and be purified through fears, doubts and perplexities, that he will be near unto deſpair, and wholly left unto the enemy, ſave onely that the Lord Jeſus privately loveth him; and ſuch a ſoul hath alſo private truſt in his mercy: and go he never ſo far, he ſhall not fall, becauſe he is born up from deſpair, though with great inward pain; ſo that he ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times knoweth not whence it cometh; and yet then that ſoul would not for all the world be blinded with the falſe love, as before it was; for that were hell to ſuch a ſoul: and this the Lord Jeſus doth in pure love, and for great profit to that ſoul, to drive out ſenſuality, that it might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive ſpiritual light. And when the ſoul is reformed in feeling, and freely accepteth the gift of perfect cleanſing, (to enter into the reſt, and ceaſe from his own works, as God did from his) then is Jeſus Chriſt more ſweetly familiar with the ſoul, (that is ſo brought through the fire of afflictions into true peace) and in this working, ſome ſouls have great devotion in prayer, and main touchings of ſpiritual light in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding; and others of comfortable heat, and great ſweetneſs, (and never come fully to this reſtful darkneſs) with a preſent fervent deſire of laſting love, and longing after God: but theſe inward feelings (where they ſtand in compunction, and ſorrow for ſin, or of devotion, or outward imagination) are not the feelings that the ſoul ſhall have, and feel in the gracious habitation with God ſpiritually, (while in this life, or body of fleſh) though they may be gracious gifts of God, and not to be abuſed or neglected, although the ſoul that feels them is not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45573:22"/>in feeling; for it hath not yet received the gift of perfect and ſpiritual burning love to Jeſus Chriſt, as they may come to, if they be faithful in it; and yet they may feel more of the love of God then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (that have that gift in the way towards perfect feeling) in as much as the feeling ſheweth more outwardly by their fervour in bodily tokens, as in weeping, praying, ſpeaking, and other bodily ſtirrings and ſtrivings, that ſome others would think them raviſhed with love, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet ſtill conſider, that theſe ſtirrings and ſtrivings are of God, to ſtay them from the worldly love, and luſts of the fleſh, that have ſo long been rooted in their hearts; from which (worldly love) they may not be drawn out by ſuch feeble ſtirrings of great fervour, and outward ſtrength, which is no true token of much love, but of weakneſs, and little love in their ſouls, that cannot bear a little touching of God; for it is yet fleſhly, and faſtened thereto, and not mortified there from by the work of the Spirit of God.—For the touch ſeems ſo quick, and alſo delectable over all things felt before in fleſhly love of earthly things, that it is over-taken with it, for that it is ſo new, ſudden and ſtrange, that the body cannot well bear it, but breaketh out into weepings, bodily ſtirrings, and other actions; as Chriſt ſaid, the <hi>old bottles</hi> would break, and not hold the <hi>new wine,</hi> but that God keepeth it whole, in mercy let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth it break out into tears, and words, through weakneſs and feeble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſoul, and not becauſe of much love, (as ſome may ſuppoſe) but afterwards, when (through love) the uncleanneſs is melted out of the ſoul, by ſuch fervour, then is the love clear, and ſtandeth ſtill; and then perfect love caſteth out fear; then is the ſoul in peace, and much more in love then before, though it ſhew leſs outward; for it is now all whole, at reſt within, and little appearing outwardly.—For in the firſt ſtate, ſuch feelings come to the ſoul ſuddainly, before it be well a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware; and as it comes before the ſoul knows it, ſo it oft returneth or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parteth without its knowledge; neither can the ſoul tell how to come to that ſtate again, no know where to find it; for the thought are not yet kept within in the light, with a firm longing deſire to Jeſus Chriſt, nor the eye of the ſoul kept open, and neer to the ſpiritual beholding of heavenly things; and ſo the heart is not ſixed: and then what weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unſuitableneſs is in all, without ſtedfaſneſs, firm faith, and full intent to God; to know his ſecrets, and obey his will?—And it is always to be diligently minded, that there are two manner of feelings; the one inward, according to mans bodily wit and skill; and the other more inward, or within that, being of ſpiritual light, wiſdom and skill, which the holy Ghoſt teacheth, and planteth in the powers of the ſoul.— So there is a meekneſs that is gained, by the working of reaſon, in fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly feeling; and another that is deeply felt in the ſoul, and is the free and ſpiritual gift of love: and it is a full hard thing, and a great my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery to him that ſtands in the working of his own reaſon, to keep conſtant reſt and ſoftneſs in his heart, and charity to love men, when they deſpiſe him; without reſiſting or repining thereat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Both theſe are of love,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45573:23"/>but the firſt worketh by the reaſon of the ſoul, the ſecond worketh by the holy Spirit in the ſoul; and ſo the firſt is imperfect, the ſecond perfect: The firſt, meekneſs, a man feeleth in beholding his ſin and wretchedneſs, and judging himſelf unworthy of any mercy, or good thing at the hand of God, and (as the worſt of creatures) worthy of all ſufferings, and thus thruſteth himſelf down under all others, and grieveth in his heart, when he is overcome by any temptation; confeſſeth, accuſeth himſelf, and asketh forgiveneſs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But this is not perfect meekneſs, for it comes of beginning to profit in grace, cauſed by beholding of ſins; and this is the meekneſs that love worketh by the reaſon of the ſoul.— But perfect meekneſs the ſoul feeleth of the ſight, and ſpiritual know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of Jeſus Chriſt, ſeeing him to be all, and do all in the ſoul, and for it, and hath ſo great love and joy in that ſpiritual ſight, that it for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getteth it ſelf, (after a ſort) and leaneth to Jeſus Chriſt with all the love it hath to behold him, and heeds not any unworthineſs or ſins be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore done, but ſetteth it ſelf with all ſins paſt, and good deeds alſo, at nought, as unworthy to be remembred; and judgeth no particular ſoul, (neither better nor worſe them himſelf) but loves and helps the good in all, and every man therein; and ſlighteth and deſpiſeth all the joy and worſhip of this world, as ſeeing it ſo little and nought, in regard of the joy and love the ſoul feeleth in the ſpiritual ſight of Jeſus Chriſt, and knowledge of his purity and holineſs, that though he might have all worldly joy, and worſhip without ſin, yet he would not meddle with it. The world hath no ſavour in this meekneſs, but is exceeding far from it. It is the lover of Jeſus Chriſt onely that hath this meekneſs abiding in him with liking and gladneſs, and that without any heavineſs, or ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for it—But the world hath a proud meekneſs, belonging to an hypocrite, (without this joy or gladneſs by the gift of the holy Ghoſt) and do heed the praiſes of men, as alſo fear their diſpraiſes, taking plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or diſpleaſure thereat in themſelves: and it's like this was the ſnare that <hi>David</hi> prayed to have his heart pluckt out of.—And many that yet love the praiſe of men more then God or his praiſe, do beſtir them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, travel and labour, with their wills, wits and affections, and ſo think on God, Chriſt, and outward exerciſes, as it were by their ſtrength to draw out of themſelves a feeling of the love of God in Chriſt, even by bodily force and maſtery, if that were poſſible. But theſe love not ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, nor is this a kindly or gracious work of love, but a kind of mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing of the ſoul at Reaſons bidding; which (without meekneſs, and forſaking the love of earthly things) is very dangerous to beget ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual pride, which otherwiſe done in meekneſs of love, and a loathing of all earthly affections, may finde favour with the Lord, and be by him changed from mans own works into ſpiritual workings: for as man can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not think a good thought of himſelf, ſo he ought to forbear his own thinkings, words and works, as not good, and therefore can find no ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance with God; and wait with patience for the Lords working in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45573:23"/>him, to will and to do, of his good pleaſure; all other workings being to the ſoul's greater ſufferings, and loſs: as the Prophet ſaid, <hi>The kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of fires with mans own sparks, cauſeth the foul to lie down in ſorrow.</hi>— In ſuch an imperfect Lover, Love worketh freely by the affections of man; but in perfect Lovers, Love worketh within, in the light, by ſpiritual af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, killing all other affections in the ſoul, and that both kindly and quietly: —but man not knowing this work of the holy Spirit, will not believe how the vertues of Meekneſs, Soberneſs, Chaſtity, Love and Cleanneſs, is wrought ſo quietly and ſurely, without travel or painful labour of the body, and bodily wits; and therefore they labour and toil day after day, with their Reaſons, and outward exerciſes, in their own ſtrength, to get vertues, and make love by words, and other ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings; and what they ſeem ſo to get, they have much more ado to keep, with all their fightings againſt ſin, contendings for grace, and wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings about it; and therefore are like Wraſtlers, ſometimes above, and ſoon again underneath; up and down, in and out, off and on, getting and loſing, and ſo weary their wits, and tire themſelves; becauſe all this ſtriving is in their own reaſon, might, and ſtrength of ſelf-will, as fightings with themſelves, but neither in true ſavour nor love, and therefore have not the victory or upper hand of what they ſtrive about; and ſuch muſt looſe the full reſt, becauſe no man may ſo put himſelf fully into Gods hands, for that man ſeeth him not; but his eye being ſhut, he thereby cloſeth it faſter, (leſt he ſhould ſee) and will not know it: and though ſome ſuch may ſuffer bodily pains for what they do, as in love to Jeſus Chriſt, and that gladly; yet being not of the holy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit (led by the fire of burning love and brightneſs) it is fully mingled with high pride, preſumption, judging and diſdaining them by whom they ſuffer; and yet theſe ſay and think they are in charity, and that they ſuffer all for the love of God; but are begailed by the Devil's transformings, becauſe their knowledge of God is principally in imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, and their love to him in natural affections, and bodily like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; at the beſt, but as milk before ſtrong meat; for in ſtrong feed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on the Father's Bread, at his own Table, the imaginations may not be ſerviceable, unleſs to the feeling in underſtanding, when need is; and then onely as a hand-maid, waiting on the hand of her Dame.</p>
            <p>Many do like well of the Vertues of Meekneſs, Lowlineſs, and Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, as in their own reaſons and wills, that are enemies thereto in their affections, through grudgings in themſelves at thoſe in whom they are; and ſo can have no love to Vertue, or vertuous men, or know how to delight in them as ſuch, ſpiritually; and what theſe men do by the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of reaſon in them, is but out of a fleſhly fear of God, (or rather applauſe of men:) for Jeſus Chriſt is but as a ſtranger to the ſoul, until his Image be therein reformed, in meekneſs and love, which is his Live<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:45573:24"/>and wherein he diſcovers himſelf and his ſecrets; as he ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>Learn of me; for I am lowly and meek, and you ſhall finde reft to your ſouls:</hi> and again, <hi>Love ye one another,</hi> or, <hi>love together as I have loved you; by this</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>ſhall all men know that you are my diſciples.</hi> He did not ſay, They ſhould be known by working miracles, caſting out Devils, preaching, teaching, or praying, which ſhould be more minded by thoſe that now deſire ſignes and wonders (that they may otherwiſe ſee if they ſhut not their eyes) while true love and meekneſs are the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of miracles in theſe laſt and perilous times, wherein men ſtrive to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt evil, (not to ſuffer it) to revenge wrongs, rather then to forgive them, as Chriſt commanded; rather to fain love and meekneſs, then be poſſeſſed of them, ſuffer and endure all things; and ſuch is not worthy the name of love or meekneſs in mans will, which is but altogether im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect: but meekneſs as in pure love and ſpiritual affections, is perfect meekneſs; and he that hath this, is a meek man, poor in ſpirit, that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth himſelf as he is, and ought to be known, diſſembleth not, but loveth all others in or for God; but where grudgings are in the heart towards any, or unquiet thoughts, the heart is not clean, the conſcience is not pure, nor the walking charitably, or with God, in love of clean affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and conſequently in and for God: for the more evil any one doth to a meek man, the more good doth he to him, as to a man out of his right minde; and ſo do thou, and pray for ſuch as Chriſt commanded, and obſerve how he himſelf did by <hi>Judas</hi> (for all his wickedneſs) and to others, never ſo much as ſaying to any man, Thou lyeſt; though ſome falſly accuſed him, ſaid, <hi>He had a devil,</hi> &amp;c. neither do I read that he reproved <hi>Judas</hi> openly, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t rather waited for his repentance to the very laſt: and the more like to Jeſus Chriſt thou art herein, the more thou loveſt thy ſelf onely in God, and not out of him, and ſo thou loveſt truly, and not onely for righteouſneſs &amp; vertue of God in thee or others; ſo thou loveſt not thy felf, but God; and if thou be yet bound in ſin, and feeleſt the burden of it, then ſo thou loveſt thy ſelf for God, to be freed by him from ſin, into his ſervice; and ſo if thou truly live in meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, thou loveſt every man; in the firſt place, thou loveſt God in man; and in the ſecond place, thou loveſt man for God; that he may be his; &amp; ſo ſhould God be loved in all, and for all, and all in him; and this is true love; but if thy minde be troubled, or unquiet when thou art rebuked, belyed, or evilly entreated, then there is pride remaining in thy heart, (ſeem thou never ſo holy outwardly) and there lyes hid like a Fox in his den;—And no good deed canſt thou poſſibly do, but it is ſpoil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therewith, and thou haſt thy reward:—for it is a myſtery to love mens perſons, (which ever ought to be) and loathe their ſins, as contrary to God; but it is no myſtery to fain or pretend love, faſt, ſit ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, preach, give to the needy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for theſe things bad men may do; but to love men truly, and hate the evil in them, is the gift of God by the holy Spirit of Love, which he gives freely and readily to all that wait
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:45573:24"/>truely for it; and is therefore moſt pretious and profitable: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this, there is not meekneſs of love to all men, and a ſeeking the ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all, but a ſtumbling and erring from the truth, and miſtaking one thing for another, errours for truth, and truth for errours; becauſe Covetouſneſs and Anger is not forſaken, while any other love (but what is ſo in God and for God) remains as to any creature or thing; and thou ſhalt ſinde it eaſier to forſake riches and luſts, then the love of them; for he that coveteth or deſireth any thing he hath not, and thereby keeps back the clean deſires to Vert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, is yet covetous; and look how much ſorrow thou feeleſt upon the loſs of any thing, ſo much was thy love to it; ſo that thou coveteſt not ſpiritual things, ſo as thou oughteſt, but that thou ſtambleſt at them; and then how ſhouldſt thou be filled with kindly ſavour within, while the fleſh retains its beaſtly ſavour without? —But this know, that diligent watching, inward hunger and pains helpeth the holy Spirit in thee to overcome; yet while the bad root lives its evil branches will be ſpringing up, for therein is the compleat nature of the evil root, and thereof the loathſome fruit, which every evil man brings forth, out of the evil treaſure of his heart, and there the ſtrong man armed keeps the houſe, until there be a free yeilding to Jeſus Chriſt in meekneſs and pure love, wherein he may overcome that ſtrong man, and ſtrip him of all his ſtrength, and weapons wherein he truſteth, and create the new man according to his own image and likeneſs of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and true holineſs; and as thou receiveſt him with ability to exerciſe thy ſences, and diſcern things rightly; to have Jeſus Chriſt formed in thee, and as thou conceiveſt him, and he lives in thee, thou wilt bring forth good things out of the good treaſure of his life, by ſtrong deſires, and earneſt actings to pleaſe him, and be made like unto him; not as of fleſhly forming, but in full meekneſs of minde, pure love, full perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and fruition of all heavenly vertues, and unchangeable bleſſedneſs, whereunto Chriſt Jeſus is the door, he the Porter, (and not another) he <hi>opens, and no man ſhuts; and ſhuts, and no man opens;</hi> by him is the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance, the going in and out, and finding paſture; for he is the paſture, even the living bread that came down from heaven, and is in heaven; the well of water ſpringing up to everlaſting life, of whom all the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ſects and ſorts of men (that climb up another way) are ignorant, and ſo (wanting the nouriſhment thereof) <hi>fall ſhort of the glory of God;</hi> and yet forward to reprove others, without any certain knowledge of thoſe things in themſelves, or conſidering with how much meekneſs, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs, love and privacie (for the moſt part) reproofs ought to be, even in weighty matters, and in all as thruſt on by divine love, and ſome hopes of thereby ſhewing the ſinner the evil of his way, that he may be reclaimed; ever weighing well how dangerous it is to abaſe and reprove others, and not live in the light ones ſelf; and how many tribulations and tentations others have born; to keep thee low in thine own eyes, and learn to know how to eſteem others highly in love for their works ſake: but
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45573:25"/>but whoſoever arrogates to, or exalts himſelf, thereby becomes baſe and blockiſh, an antichriſt, unfit for any ſpiritual work, and ſhall cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall low at laſt, becauſe the power of the Lord Jeſus hath not had a kindly working in ſuch a ſoul, or his pure preſence received by it, or rightly known to it, to live and grow up in it; as it is in all meek ſouls, that in a ſtill and quiet ſtaidneſs ſuffer him, and yeild to him, for the increaſe and finiſhing of his own work therein.</p>
            <p>The Soul of Man, which the LORD GOD formed (as hath been ſaid) by breathing of his breath of life into him, is a worthy likeneſs, image, or ſimilitude of God; — not the bodily ſhape, but the inner powers thereof; — but ſince falling from the light and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly preſence of ſweet love, and ſure joy, into the painful darkneſs and luſts of this wretched life, is by his own act caſt out of the heritage of heaven: So that man now in no wiſe can know Jeſus Chriſt <hi>(the Lamb of God that taketh away the ſin of the world)</hi> by running out with his thoughts into the moſt excellent way that mans wit can imagine, but by a turning the Soul in to that of God within it ſelf, in the light thereof, and there waiting for his ſtill voice, wherein the Lord Jeſus Chriſt moveth;— which the wiſe and prudent men of this world imagine to be a low, mean, natural and contemptible thing; but therein is the living and true God diſcovered to the ſoul, and exalted above all created things, whereby the ſoul ſeeth it ſelf, and alſo above it ſelf into the heavenly place; while it is ſo kept in the moſt inner and precious clean part of it ſelf, and taketh pure pleaſure therein, and that not onely for the light ſake, but for the bleſſed love which is in that light, and the knowledge it giveth how to ſeek God within, and forget all bodily things without, and alſo forget thinking of it ſelf, and wayting to finde therein, onely the uncreated God, that made him, and gave him reaſon, will and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and quickeneth him in Chriſt Jeſus by his bleſſed light; and ſo as Chriſt Jeſus moves in him by his grace, ſo moveth the ſoul to find and feel him more in himſelf, as the true light, which is not a natural or bodily thing, but truth and faithfulneſs in ſpiritual light; for as bodily light ſerveth to the body, or outward man, ſo this true light, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſpiritual being (which is God in Chriſt) ſheweth to the reaſon of the ſoul, firſt it ſelf, and then in and by it ſelf, all other ſpiritual things that are needful to the knowledge and ſalvation of the Soul: So ſaid <hi>David, By,</hi> or, <hi>In thy light we ſee light:</hi> And thus is God <hi>a conſuming fire,</hi> that burneth and conſumeth ſin out of the ſoul, and purifieth it, even as fire parifieth Metals; and theſe are as favory words (as alſo is the work) to thoſe that ſo receive them; and when the inner eye of the Soul is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened through grace, to have ſuch a beholding of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſhall the ſoul be raught to turn the outward powers into ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual uſe; and not to reft in a bare believing, but grow in farther
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:45573:26"/>ſight and knowledge of him, untill the reaſonable ſoul receive the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God (as Chriſt ſaid) and that full bleſſed and endleſs life in him.—And in order thereto, ever to feel and know how Jeſus Chriſt opens the inner eye of the ſoul, of his goodneſs and meer mercy, when and as he pleaſeth, by lighting the reaſon with his true inner light in the conſcience to ſee him, and know him by little and little, as the ſoul may ſuffer him; whereby he gently ſheweth the ſoul that he is an unchangeable being, of ſaving ſtrength, faithfulneſs, good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and bleſſedneſs of endleſs life, which the obedient ſoul learneth to ſee (as much more then can be well expreſs'd) as Jeſus pleaſeth to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veal to him by his holy Spirit, and that not blindly, nakedly, or unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourily, as in mans own reaſon (by his outward learning or other bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly abilities) but with an underſtanding enlightned, comforted and ſtrengthened by the gift of the holy Ghoſt, with a wonderfull inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſible love, reverence, godly fear, ſpirituall ſavour, and heavenly delight; ſo as that the affections become raviſhed therewith, and keeps from the minding of earthly things: And thus is Go! pleaſed to beget his owne likeneſs in man, which beg tring is his Son in fleſh, even that goodneſs, ſight, and ſure knowledge of God in Chriſt, and love unfained in him, which is a reforming of the ſoul in faith and feeling, and yet may not be grown ſo fully perfect in love, as ſome have felt and written of; but the more clean, clear and ſimple the ſoul is made in parting from fleſhly love, the more quick ſight and greater love to God it hath; and it may be ſo, as though there were no other man, that believed in, or loved Jeſus Chriſt, but that he were alone (as <hi>Elijah</hi> once thought) yet he would love him, truſt in him and follow him, and not part with him for all other things; and then a man valueth all earthly created things at one rate, as nothing worth in his eſteem, knowing that both the love and the things themſelves (that worldly men eſteem and delight in) ſhall periſh together,— coveting nothing but cloſe communion with Jeſus Chriſt ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally; not fleſhly, for he knows not after the fleſh, but loves and owns Jeſus Chriſt in all men, without reſpect to outward perſons and things, and flies from the vain ſights of worldly delights, that others take plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in, his delight being onely in Jeſus Chriſt, leſt other things ſhould let the freedome of his heart from him; neither doth he value or heed the ſpeakings of other men, unleſs in the ſame light, love &amp; meekneſs of Jeſus Chriſt; and would rather be ſtill in peace, having nothing outwardly, unleſs it be ſpoken feelingly and ſtirringly, as of the love of Jeſus to farther him therein.—And as for ſpeaking or hearing of worldly ſpeech, it hath no ſavour in him, much leſs ſtories, tidings, or vain janglings, can have no place in his thoughts, and therefore not in his affections; for as the inner eye of the ſoul is opened through faith, working by love, into the beholding of Jeſus Chriſt by inſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſpeciall grace, it is thereby made clean, ſubtill, and able to
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:45573:27"/>move to, and work in the Lords vineyard, in ſuch manner of working by the holy Ghoſt, as the greateſt learned men on earth cannot ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, with all their wit and skill, much leſs ſhew it with their tongues; becauſe it is not gotten by ſtudy, nor through any mans labour, but by pure and ſpeciall gift of the holy Ghoſt; and is not different in quality from the heavenly gift in converſion of the choſen ſouls, but is the ſame, though it be otherwiſe felt and ſhadowed out to the ſoul— For as the ſoul groweth in grace, ſo grace groweth in the ſoul, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth more and more unto the perfect day, and heavenly kingdom of eſpeciall ſeeing into the ſecrets of the Lord Jeſus; ſo that when the heart awaketh to God, and is knit to him, then it ſleepeth, and is loſt from the world: And thus the Apoſtles ſlept to the worldly love, while in true inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, contemplating on Jeſus Chriſt, they were awake (though they had other ſleeps, ſometimes, as when Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Could you not watch with me one houre?</hi>) having their ſouls inſpired through grace, and the ſpeciall eye therein opened, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding Jeſus Chriſt in purity and poverty of ſpirit, inward ſilence, true reſt, peace in conſcience, highneſs of heavenly thoughts, with ſingleneſs and purity of heart, diſliking the joyes of this world, and onely delighted with ſpirituall ſavour of bright burning love; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting for, and gently ſeeking the Lords bleſſed preſence ſpiritually. Theſe are true teſtimonies of the inſpiration of the holy Ghoſt, in this keeping the ſpirituall eye of the ſoul; but ſeeing that reforming one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in faith, and fleſhly feeling is very low and perilous in its begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning (becauſe of the aptneſs then to yield to the tempter and back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlide) and reforming in ſpirituall feeling and ſavour ſo high and ſure, great diligence is requiſite in watching, waiting, coveting, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring (as the Lord Jeſus moveth) in diſpoſing the affections, and bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the heart to cleanneſs and feeling of grace, which is a conſtant work, of much travel of ſoul againſt all wicked ſtirrings and tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; for it ſo falls out with ſome, that through negligence and yiel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to tentations, the enemy enters the ſoul again; and then it feels not the grace as it did, but it is withdrawn, and the ſoul returns into the ſtate as before; but then the ſoul is in much blindneſs, pain, ſorrow and unſavourineſs; for it reliſheth worldly things but unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourily, and is encumbered with bodily wit and earthly matters for the time; and then it deſireth after the grace of Chriſt Jeſus again, and may not find it for a time: but this withdrawing is alwayes for juſt cauſe, and alſo in much merey to prove the ſoul, and let it ſee that without Chriſt it can do nothing, and come to him again with much pain and labour, fear, care, and watchfulneſs; while it ſuppoſeth that Jeſus Chriſt heareth not, which is his dealing with many, for their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall ſtrength and growth in him; for then the Lord Jeſus is ſure that the ſoul will not turn again to worldly love, for that it can have no ſavour therein; and then after a time Jeſus Chriſt returneth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:45573:25"/>that ſoul full of grace and truth; viſiteth it in its deſires, ſighs and longings, for very love to his preſence; and then as he toucheth it ſoftly, and <hi>anoynieth</hi> it with the <hi>oyle of gladneſs,</hi> it is healed of all pains and pantings, and then it cryeth to Jeſus in the ſpirit, with a glad heart and ſweet ſtill voyce, as his love teacheth.</p>
            <p>This opening of the ſpirituall eye of the ſoule, is a light darkneſle, and rich poverty, leading to purity of ſpirit, quietneſs of conſcience, inward peace and ſpirituall reſt, with high and heavenly thoughts, in ſingleneſs of ſoul, a light and feeling of grace in the ſecrets of the heart,— taſting heavenly ſavour of inflamed love, with bright-ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning light, of reforming into pure feeling, whereof many holy men of God have written every one according to his reſpective feeling thereof in the grace of the holy Ghoſt; and though they ſeem divers in ſhewing by words (becauſe then each one ſpake after his own, then receiving and encreaſing in grace) yet nevertheleſs they agreed in all, as in one ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of unchangable verity;— for the ſoul that (through the Lords mercifull viſiting with his grace) comes to ſee the face of Jeſus by that touching and eſpeciall grace of the holy Ghoſt, is changed and turned from what it was into another manner of living, for it is wonderfully drawn; firſt into it ſelf, from love and likings of all earthly things, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that it hath loſt the ſavour of the bodily life, and all things elſe, ſave onely Jeſus Chriſt; and is thereby made clean from all the filth of ſin, and all inordinate affections are wiped off, and waſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the blood of the Lamb, and hath nothing ſtanding to hinder him (between God and his ſoul) but onely the bodily eye, which is thereby become blind, and the ſoul in ſpirituall reſt with Jeſus Chriſt, without fears, cares or deſires of worldly things, but fully imployed in a free and ſpiritual working, and love therein; whereby its reſt increaſeth to perfection; it being truly called reſt, becauſe grace hath wholly loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the heavy yoak and bonds of fleſhly love, to work with eaſe in ſweet amity, joy and delight, as the holy Spirit directeth the ſoul and leadeth it:—And this doth ſilence the ſoul from janglings of all other ſpeakers; — for it is the voyce of Jeſus Chriſt in heavenly vertue, ſoftly ſounding in the clean ſoul by his quick and piercing word (ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dividing between the joynts and marrow, and diſcerning the thoughts and intents of the heart) that ſlayeth all fleſhly love, and keepeth the ſoul quiet from all the ſtirrings thereof, and ſo is ſilence made in heaven for half an hour (as it is written) even within in the clean ſoul, that is lifted up by grace, from earthly love to heavenly converſation; and ſo it is in ſilence, though but for a ſhort time before it be again aſſaulted by its enemies;— yet hath it peace in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, becauſe this grace puts out all gratings, prickings, ſtirrings and fightings of ſin, making Jeſus Chriſt and the ſoul both one in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:45573:26"/>of will and affections, ſo that there are no upbraidings of ſin, nor reprovings for faults;—for the Son and that ſoul have kiſſed each other, and are become friends, and all faults paſt are forgiven, whereby the ſoul feeleth aſſurance of its ſalvation (by the witneſs of the holy Ghoſt in the heart) and thereby receiveth day by day more and more ſpirituall joy and boldneſs to come to the throne of grace, the holy Spirit bearing witneſs of its ſonſhip, and the witneſs in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence adminiſtring ſure conſolation, with peace and pure accord, love and laſting friendſhip between Jeſus Chriſt and the ſoul, ſo that the ſoul is then above the world in high and heavenly contemplation, which is an earneſt of true glory here in the body, in the knowledge of Jeſus Chriſt, with ſo ſtrong and laſting deſires of love, that many waters cannot quench;— And bleſſed is that ſoul which is ever fed in feeling of love in Jeſus Chriſts preſence, &amp; is born up by deſire to him in his abſence; for he is wiſe and hath well learned Chriſt, that holdeth him ſadly and reverently with pure affections, while he is preſent; and while he is as abſent, beareth it patiently and eaſily, without bitter pains of impure deſires;— and as there are diverſities of feelings in the preſence of grace, ſo there are in the abſence of grace, according to the ſouls meekneſs or growth therein; and therefore he that knoweth not the abſence of grace, is readily deceived by outward ſounds of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens ſayings;— and he that is not diligent and watchfull to keep the preſence of grace, is very unkind to Jeſus Chriſt, that in and for love giveth it; for the ſoul ſhould be like her head in vertue and firmneſs of perfect love.— And this take for a maxime—that he who perceiveth no changes in feeling of his grace given him, but ſtill remains a like, all whole, ſtrong, ſtable, unbroken, or unhurt (as he thinketh) muſt needs be either full perfect, or full blind; but the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is more like, or moſt to be feared; for he that is ſo perfect, that he is above all touches of earthly things, dwelleth in Jeſus Chriſt by ſweet and ſoft love, is accepted into a high eſtate of heavenly glory and reſtfull pleaſure, knowing nothing but pure love, which is God;— but he is full blind indeed, that feigneth himſelf to be in grace and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour with Jeſus Chriſt, without ſpirituall feeling of the holy Ghoſt, and ſetleth himſelf in a ſtay'd condition, as if he were ever in feeling &amp; working in ſpirituall grace, thinking that all is grace that he feeleth, without and within, and that what he doeth and ſpeaketh is grace, and that he is unchangable therein,— and alwayes at one ſtay and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, which he eſteemeth good:— Such a ſoul is fully blind, and altogether without feeling of grace in any its workings; for they are wrought as aforeſaid, and by a lively inſpiration thereof, with the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall preſence of Jeſus Chriſt in the ſoul, and ſweetneſs of his love, by his wonderfull in-dwelling there. This is the life of feeling in grace (after the meaſure of the gift) with a reverend beholding him ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, without which (in ſome meaſure) all is but deceitfull, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:45573:33"/>worth, nor any way of good uſe, but hurtfull; for as the ſoul is the light and life of the body, ſo is Jeſus Chriſt the light and life of the ſoul, by his gracious preſence, which cannot ſo well be expreſt as felt; for it is the light, life, love, joy, ſtrength and reſt of the ſoul that hath painfully felt it; yet with ſweetneſs, inſomuch that it cannot ceaſe from deſiring it:— And this is, that no man may miſtake in or concerning the work of grace in his own ſoul; and he who will remain ſtill filthy, may bear his own burthen (whatever he be) and his ſhame alſo; for God hath not left himſelf without a witneſs in every man, neither is he wanting to any, though (as Chriſt ſaid) The holy Ghoſt inſpireth where and when he will, and that privily (as the wind blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) oft-times when men are leaſt aware of him, but is known by his ſtirring and turning the heart into a beholding of his goodneſs, and melting it into ſoftneſs of love, &amp; yet wondereth at his highneſs &amp; ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning brightneſs: but the ſubſtance &amp; effect of this ſhining grace remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth (though not in its fervour) while the ſoul is kept clean without fallings (by wilfulneſs or negligence) into a diſſolute life of fleſhlineſs and outward vanity;— and alſo know, that the ſoul which is unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the touches of ſpirituall grace, is an enemy to all ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall works, as being old, dry, rotten, barren, and without ſavour in it ſelf; for the ſalt hath there no ſavour, and to be trodden under foot, and nothing but the light of grace (through touching) maketh it lively, ſharp, quick, ſubtil, ready and able to ſpirituall work, by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving it great freedome, and a holy readineſs in will and affections to obey all the ſtirrings of grace in the ſoul, and to watch thereto for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening of the ſpirituall eye, whereby it becomes apt to meditation, watching and prayer, but not to pray in the common manner it did before, with loud voyce, many words, and other mens ſpeakings, but in ſtilneſs of the voyce, and tenderneſs of heart, &amp; being gathered up into it ſelf, and in the ſpirituall preſence of Jeſus Chriſt, wherein every word and ſyllable hath a ſavoury ſweet ſound, and delectable melody in the heart by the holy Spirit; as being wholly entered into the fire of love, the powers of the ſoul being all heated and inflamed with love, ſo that the ſparks flie upward, whence the fire came; and therein is the ſoul ſo comfortably enlightned, that it knowes not how to leave off watching, praying, and praiſing God, with ſpirituall delight and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly joy, when no matter is ſeen outwardly, nor voyce heard: And this is the food and nouriſhment of the ſoul, and of much vertue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt temptations and likings of the world; for it beareth up both ſoul and body from painfull heavineſs of heart, and feeling of the wretched<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this earthly life, and the ſoul is thereby kept quick and lively: This was <hi>Davids</hi> prayer as Incenſe aſcending and perfuming the ſoul, and ſo as any hath a Pſalm of the ſpirit, which is ſavoury and ſoft, ſweet and pleaſant, in the pure mind, broken and burning heart, it giveth up a ſweet ſmell to the face of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt: theſe
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:45573:34"/>are the prayers and praiſes, heard and accepted of God, (as before hath been ſaid) yielding and alſo receiving grace from him, which he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts as an addition to his Glory; and all other praying wants ſavour and ſweetneſs, as a ſpeaking of words with the tongue, when the heart is gone after other lovers, or likings of fleſhly things, and the ſoul is not maſter of the bodily wits, and imaginations of the brain, and is that wherein is no conſtant devotion, no free<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om of ſpirit, no ardent and burning love and affections, nor whole mind; but much ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and running about here and there by words (ſeeming to ſpeak of ſpirituall matters) without ſavour, profit, or any ſoul-ſatisfaction, and therefore hear with me a few words more of this weighty buſineſs of Prayer, and keep firſt to ſilence and firm watchfulneſs, that thou maiſt firſt come to a joyfull feeling of this ſpirituall praying, and that ſhall teach thee unchangable wiſdome, without fancy or faine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs (that thoſe are poſſeſſed with that ſpeak well or ill of things they know not) and therefore abide therein, untill grace come into thy ſoul otherwiſe, and will remove it in part for a time, and employ thee otherwiſe; and then therein be obedient, for that is the beſt of all ſacrifices, whereby the holy God will be ſerved; and ſo there is no need of mans teaching how to pray or praiſe him, what words to ſpeak, how to divide duties into parts, or to guide the affections; for the holy Spirit teacheth all this, and much more, as he pleaſeth; and the ſoul feeleth it ſelf led thereby to enjoy Jeſus Chriſt in ſome meaſure: but this praying and praiſing God with the Spirit and underſtanding, the wiſe world ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts fooliſhneſs, and (being ſtrangers to it) would have others continue ſo likewiſe. In this ſpirituall watchfulneſs is the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, whereby the writings of the holy men of God are rightly ſhewed and opened, which mans wit, learning, reaſon, or ſtudy, cannot reach; for the underſtanding thereof is freely ſhewed to the clear ſoul by Jeſus Chriſt, who is the well-ſpring of wiſdome and knowledge; it is he that maketh the ſoul lively, and wiſe to underſtand the holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, and yet not all at once in ſpeciall view thereof, but grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth ability in ſpirituall manner, as it cometh into the pure mind: and this opening of the underſtanding is by the working of the holy Ghoſt in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſence of Jeſus Chriſt, whereby the ſoul is enabled to expound the Scriptures one after another, be they never ſo hard or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret; and the harder they be, and the farther from mans reaſon and underſtanding, the more delightfull is the true ſhewing of them, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be Literal, as concerning the outward man; Moral, to inform of vertues to be followed, and vices to be eſchewed; Myſtical, to ſee the words and works of Jeſus Chriſt ſpiritually; or Spirituall, as longing after him and his works, to do them in like love, and live in them as his friends (ſo ſaid he) and this laſt truly underſtanding Scriptures ſavours well, and very ſweetly in the Lords taſte; for ſo the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of life giveth underſtanding of what was formerly by himſelf dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:45573:27"/>and from him written (and ſo of no private interpretation) quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the thoughts of the ſoul therein with great ſweetneſs, ſavour and delight, in ſpecial, ſad, and ſerious waiting on Jeſus Ghriſt, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand Scriptures in his will, and his teſtimonies of love therein, through divers inward diſcernings, ſweet movings, and ſudden touchings of the holy Ghoſt, whereby the ſoul is taught and enabled thereto, without other helps; and he that thus is given to underſtand the Scriptures, values not the knowledge of men, gotten by learning, arts and ſci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, though of never ſo great worldly cunning and skill; for the end of the true knowledge thereof, taught by Jeſus Chriſt, is, that the ſoul may ſee and enjoy him, and attain ſalvation to life eternall, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in glorifie him, as God equall with the Father, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> whereas the other way of knowledge is for ſelf-ends, worldly vanities, and fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights.</p>
            <p>When the ſervants of Jeſus Chriſt are well skilled concerning their hearing the voyce of Chriſt, they truly hearken, know, and follow him; and then neither feignedneſs (by transformings, nor otherwiſe) can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them; for therein is no fainedneſs, fancy, pride, nor hypocriſie, but ſoundneſs, meekneſs, peace and charity, full of life, love and grace; ſo that when it ſoundeth in the ſoul, it ſo aboundeth with ſtrength and vertue, that it cauſeth the ſoul to leave all to wait upon it, to liſten, hearken, perceive, reſt in, and love the ſweet breathing of his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall voyce, according as he ſheweth himſelf, whether as a Maſter, a Father, a Husband, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> keeping the ſoul in a wonderfull reverence and lively beholding of him, with much liking and delight to the ſoul, that it may become a true and faithfull Spouſe to him in the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of fellowſhip, and light of love:— and this is in great power and glory, a ſtate of perfection, in the way to as full communion with God, as <hi>Adam</hi> had in innocency, and <hi>Enoch</hi> by walking with him— but the ſight, ſtrength and comforts of ſome are therein more then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, though all in this ſtate are growing into the love and life of God in Chriſt Jeſus, ſo as the eye of heaven is opened to all ſuch clean ſouls, whereof holy men have diverſly written, as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt, as of a life above all appearances, likeneſſes, bodily crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or things, even as in heaven beholding the Lord Jeſus ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and loving him faithfully, and therein knowing God the holy Ghoſt, as love uncreated, and the love formed in the affections of the ſoul, to be of and by him, through the ſight and knowledge of the unchangable light and truth, which is of God placed and ſeated in all meek ſouls, wherein the ſpirit of holineſs reſteth and pleaſantly wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth;— pet this formed love in the ſoul is not God himſelf, but the love which the ſoul feeleth in Jeſus Chriſt, and to him; neither is this the cauſe of coming to Jeſus Chriſt, but pure love, which is God
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:45573:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:28"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:29"/>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:45573:29"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:45573:30"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:30"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:31"/>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:45573:31"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:45573:32"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:32"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:33"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:34"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:35"/>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:45573:35"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:45573:36"/>himſelf, is the true cauſe of this knowing and drawing to himſelf; for he ſheweth and giveth of this love (which is the holy Ghoſt) to teach and lead therein, ſo that God is both the giver and the gift, as Chriſt Jeſus ſaid, <hi>I give my life,</hi> &amp;c. whereby mans ſoul comes to know this uncreated love, and to know and love Jeſus Chriſt, as the free gift of God, whereby he toucheth the heart with the inviſible light, to know him, and receive his love, and to love him again, as in and with the ſame love (ſo freely given and received) but all in his own time, by more quick or flow gracious feelings, imparted into ſuch ſouls as are cloathed with the new light of righteouſneſs and true holineſs, which is a right reforming in this ſpirituall ſavour, love and meekneſs; but he is not ſo lighted and led by the holy Spirit, that thinks he can do any good thing of himſelf, or otherwiſe then by ſuch working in him ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually.</p>
            <p>To you my dear friends, that are of the holy brethren, partakers of the heavenly vocation, I ſalute you in the pure light of unchangable and endleſs love in Chriſt Jeſus our Lord, according to the ſpirit of holineſs, and undefiled liberty, wherewith he hath made us free, to ſerve him in ſpirit and truth;—have you born the indignation of the Lord in your own particulars?—are you purged from the pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of the world, cleanſed from the filthineſs of fleſh and ſpirit, and thereby departed from the ſhadowes of this world, and received glorious garments of the Lord; put off the mortall, and put on the immortall cloathing, and ſweetly confeſſed, and meekly ſuffered for the name and teſtimony of our Lord Jeſus, who is our life, and who of very faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and pure love hath cauſed us to be troubled, and is near at hand to ſuccour you and give you reſt in him, purifie and prepare you for further trials, to your ſpirituall profit and advantage, in filling up the meaſure of his ſufferings in your fleſh, and overcoming by the blood of the Lamb, the word of his teſtimony, and not loving your lives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death, wherein the eternall God will be your refuge, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneath his everlaſting arm for your defence; and therefore all to be faithfull and diligent, that truth ſuffer not by any faint or feeble ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of it; for we are not called onely to believe, but to ſuffer alſo for him in whom we believe; and you be here onely as pilgrims and ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers that have freely parted with your owne wills, deſires, fleſhly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, and worldly delights (that the eternall will of God may be done in you and by you) and now bear the Croſs quietly and patiently, in clean veſſels, as Temples of the living God, for his worſhip in the beauty of holineſs;—and what have you here more that is worthy your minding, that man can take from you? or how may you withhold any other thing from our Lord, or his ſervice, wherein you know that your loſs or labour will not be in vain? And therefore gird up the
<pb facs="tcp:45573:36"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:45573:37"/>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:45573:37"/>loyns of your minds, ſtand faſt, quit you like men, and be ſtrong in the Lord, and the power of his might, that the fear of man, careful thought, or immoderate deſire, be not found in any of you; watch and pray, that you enter not into tentations, or give occaſion to the enemy of your ſouls, leſt there ſhould be floath, guile, or diſſimulation hid in any heart, or a root of bitterneſs ſpringing up, to trouble and defile, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unskilfull ſtirring by inordinate affections, in any ſoul after the bodily ſufferings; changes being ſeldome free from temptations, ſpecially in the weak, who are moſt apt to cenſure the ſtrong; he that hath the beam in his own eye, to pull at the moat that is in his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers eye: while contrarily the ſtrong ſtrive not with the weakneſs in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but ever to ſtrengthen the pure principle, &amp; help it over the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that you may appeare (as you are) the plant which the Lords right hand hath planted, ſo as that none can pluck you up, his portion and peculiar treaſure, his Jewels, ſons of the free woman, that abide in the houſe for ever; a people whom the Lord loves, leads about, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructs in his way, and keeps from evil, and to whom is his bleſſing of peace and life for evermore; that are as living ſtones built up a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all houſe, as a city ſet on a hill, that cannot be hid, to ſhew forth his praiſe in the bleſſed love and brightneſs of his ſhining glory, and be a ſweet ſavour to him in them that believe, and in them that periſh in unbelief; by holding forth the faithfull word of his patience, and ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Goſpel of mans ſalvation, &amp;c. What manner of perſons ought you therefore to be in all holy converſation, that by the burning beams of his beautifull and holy preſence, you may put to ſilence the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of fooliſh men, that blame your good converſation in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and the hearts of others (that tremble at the word of the Lord) be melted into tender love and heavenly ſweetneſs, ſuitable to receive that bleſſed Goſpel of peace and reconciliation, and ſo ſuck at the breaſts of conſolation, as to be daily delighted with the freſh ſprings of his love, thereby to flouriſh as an herb, and be prepared to enjoy the inheritance of the Saints in light;—and though the world know you not, and Satan (the enemy of your ſouls) would not have you known (leſt it ſhould be to his loſs) yet is the righteous God (greater in you then he that is in the world) haſting to clear up your innocency, that you may be well known to have no ſtrange god amongſt you, that you touch not the unclean thing, but are his ſons and daughters, having your habitation in the holy mountain, with the ſhout of a King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, and that his word ſpoken ſhall ſurely come to paſs, your enemies be found liars, and confeſs that they have dealt unworthily with you, for the Lord hath kindled a fire that ſhall proceed out of your mouthes to devoure the adverſary (which cannot be quenched) and they that hurt you muſt be ſo killed, and there is no project to prevent it; but as you are faithfull to our Lord, ſpirituall victory you ſhall have over the beaſt, over his image, over his mark, and over the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:45573:38"/>number of his name, and be found without ſpot before the throne of God and the Lamb;—and this is it that giveth you victory, even your firm faith; but you have need of patience, and that it have its perfect work in you, ſo that (having done the will of God) you may enjoy the promiſes in the new heaven and earth, the true voyce of God in ſpirituall glory, in the eſſentiall freedome of will, and reſtitution of all things into the heavenly reſt, wherein all doubts are reſolved, un on cleared, and expectations ſatisfied: and in the way every one is to take care there be no giving or taking offence, no falling our, no touching of any unclean thing, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y ſtriving with the evil nature in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (for that (as pitch) will defile) no giving place to evil, but over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it with good (as our Lord commanded) and being ever apt to teach and bleſs, that you may be heirs of the bleſſing.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, here is nakedly and barely ſet before all ſorts of men the wayes and wages (as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſometimes ſaid) of good and evil, life and death, for every man to chuſe which he will; for ſo it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the Lord to deal with every man, and therein he doth man no wrong, by leaving him to his own will, and giving him a reward ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his own works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and experience teacheth that every man will ſay, he loves God and Chriſt, and would be ſorry elſe (while he acts as his enemie againſt him) and that he would have everlaſting life, his ſoul ſaved by partaking of the joyes of heaven, and avoyding the torments of hell; and therefore would <hi>die the death of the righteous,</hi> and have his <hi>latter end like his.</hi>—And ſo ſaid <hi>Baalam</hi> when he was ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to curſe the people of God, and gave wicked counſel to the King of <hi>Moab</hi> againſt them; and to ſuch I ſay, Why walk you then in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laams</hi> way for mens favours &amp; rewards &amp; ſo act againſt the Lord, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and the light of him in your own conſciences, for ſelf-ends; and make ſuch proviſion for the fleſh to fulfill the luſts thereof? And why are you not now willing to live the life of the righteous, but have him in ſo great deriſion, and a proverb of reproach (as at this day) why do you account his life madneſs, and his end without honour? why erre you ſo from the truth, that the light of righteouſneſs ſhould not ariſe and ſhine in you, but reſt your ſouls ſo in fleſhly likings, and love of this world, whereby godlineſs ſeems nothing to you, but as a ſcornfull thing of nought, and wrath reſts in your hearts, even againſt the Lord and his ſervants though you ſay you love him; but know, that for all theſe things, the Lord God will bring you to judgement, &amp; you ſhall ſee (as it is written) the righteous ſtand with great boldneſs, and his ſalvation ſeem ſtrange to you, above all you looked for; and then (over-late you may ſay within your ſelves, What hath pride profited us, or the pomp of riches (with our vaunting) brought us? when the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gods you now ſerve ſhall depart as a ſhadow, or Poſt that paſſeth by,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:45573:38"/>with the friendſhip of this world, whereby you are at enmity with God; for (as it is written) whoſoever will be a friend to this world is the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy of God, and afraid of him, ſeeks to hide his heart from him, and inward fear poſſeſſeth him (as it did <hi>Adam</hi>) ſo that he hates his light, loves darkneſs, keeps in it, flies, wanders, ſtumbles, ſtaggers, and peace departeth from him; and though he force to himſelf a kind of counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit mirth for a time, yet therewith alſo he is ſoon pinched, and feels a heavy weight and pain in his own boſom, from which he cannot fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, but it reproves him and condemns him at every turn; and as for the light that ſhineth in the dark place of his ſoul, he is afraid of that alſo, and faith or love find no room in his earthen veſſel; for his own luſts fill up the place, and devour all, by conceit, imaginations, and vile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, wherein he ſpends his time to beaſt himſelf, and yet got ſwelling words of vanity, touching things he never ſaw, and to have mens perſons in admiration for advantage ſake; which is a knowledge and condition that puff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th up the heart (but redeems not to God from the worldly glory and vain converſation) wherein ſome are ſo fettered that they will not be reclaimed, or endure to be ſoberly admoniſhed to the contrary for the ſafety of their ſouls; from whence there is this one onely way, <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (the pure path to be known ſpiritually) and the Father worſhipped in him;—to which a very plain ſimple man (as the fiſhermen without humane learning) may eaſily attain, if he hinder not himſelf by his own willing, ſeeking, deſiring, hearing, ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, or outward contention about it; becauſe there is a pure princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in every mans conſcience, which hath onely need to be awaked, ſtirred up, and quickned to behold and ſee all things, in the inner pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and parts of the ſoul, and ſo ceaſe from all outward ſeekings for it, becauſe it is there the free gift of God by his ſpirit, and ſuch as no man can fully teach the knowledge of to another (though he were never ſo well acquainted with the Divine Myſteries) which if well conſidered by thoſe that have attained to ſome ſmall meaſure or degree of grace, they world not ſo run into words as many do, or be ſo conceited of their little grace received, as to loſe it by vain glory, while others that have much more, wait in ſtill ſilence of their ſouls for the Lords work, to be therein accompliſhed, as theſe alſo would (oft times when they ſpeak) did they know how little grace or ſpirituall favour they have, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of what God giveth to others (that ſingly wait on him with holy and humble hearts) and may give alſo to them, if they likewiſe wait diligently for it—Ah that worldly and vain minded men would, at laſt, conſider and commune with their own hearts, to finde out their wayes, and ſee the ſadneſs of their conditions, with the high concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their ſouls, and how the difference ſtands between the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of this world (that are wife in their generation) and the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of light, and how the latter exceed the former by many degrees of true wiſdome from above, and heavenly joy, when no word is ſpoken, or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:45573:39"/>matter ſeen outwardly; whereof may be ſome directions found (ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to each mans preſent condition) in what is here written (according to my underſtanding in the ſimple and unchangable truth) that hath a willing heart to embrace the appearances of Jeſus Chriſt ſpiritually in his own particular; — and if not, here is over-much ſaid to riſe up in judgement againſt him, when God ſhall judge the ſecrets of men by Jeſus Chriſt, according to his Goſpel, who is the Lord of Life and Glory.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>22. of the ſecond moneth, 1661.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:45573:39"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
